<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A historicall relation of the famous siege of the citie called the Busse Herevnto is added a generall mappe of the whole campe and siege, with particular mappes of all the seuerall approches in euery quarter. Compyled togeather and designed according to the iust measure and rule of geometrie by Iames Prempart, ingener to his Majestie of Sweden.</title>
            <author>Prempart, Jacques.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121882</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857041</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857041</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22709</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22709)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1033:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A historicall relation of the famous siege of the citie called the Busse Herevnto is added a generall mappe of the whole campe and siege, with particular mappes of all the seuerall approches in euery quarter. Compyled togeather and designed according to the iust measure and rule of geometrie by Iames Prempart, ingener to his Majestie of Sweden.</title>
                  <author>Prempart, Jacques.</author>
                  <author>Hondius, Hendrik, b. 1573, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32, [2] p., [10] folded plates : maps  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Printed by Ian Fredericksz Stam] for Henrico Hondio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXX. [1630]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The maps are by Hendrik Hondius, who signs some of them.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf bears "A list of our noblemen, vollunteirs, and gentlemen of our nation, which bore armes and trayled pikes at the siege of the Busse".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>'s-Hertogenbosch (Netherlands) --  History --  Siege, 1629 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>'s-Hertogenbosch (Netherlands) --  Maps --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A HISTORICALL RELATION Of the famous Siege of the Citie <hi>CALLED THE</hi> BVSSE.</p>
            <p>Herevnto is added a generall Mappe of the whole Campe and Siege, with particular Mappes of all the ſeuerall Approches in euery Quarter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Compyled togeather and deſigned according to the iuſt meaſure and rule of Geometrie BY</hi> IAMES PREMPART, Ingener to his Majeſtie of Sweden.</p>
            <p>AT AMSTERDAM, For Henrico Hondio. M.DC.XXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WHereas I perceaue that as yet none haue taken in hande to ſet forth any thing for the content of deſirous ſpirits, touching the famous Siege of the <hi>BVSSE:</hi> and that this Siege vvas ſo remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable and vvorthy as euer vvas knovvne, I haue thought good to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte vnto you, that which I haue gotten as vvell by my ovvne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience in the ſaid Siege, as that vvhich J haue from the principall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geners. And for the better explayning of the particulars, I haue placed in this Hiſtoricall Relation firſt a Mappe of tvvoo greate Leaues, conteyning the vvhole Siege vvith all the circumferences. Secondly a greate Leafe repreſenting the ſcituation of the Citie, vvith the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of euery Quarter. Thirdly here follovve Mappes of the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall approches in euery Quarter, and of the Princes Quarter ſet forth in tvvoo Leaues, by reaſon the moſt force, charge and labour paſſed there, and becauſe the Citie vvas vvonne there by degrees, vvhich is alltogeather compyled and ſet forth according to the iuſt meaſure vvith greate care and induſtrie, as by the Mappes more at large may appeare, vvhich I hope vvill be acceptable and pleaſing to you.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_soldiers">
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:2"/>
            <head>A LIST OF OUR NOBLEMEN, VOLLUNTEIRS, and Gentlemen of our Nation, which bore Armes and trayled Pikes at the Siege of the BUSSE, vnder the foure Engliſh Coronells Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, and firſt of thoſe which were vnder my Lord Generall Vere his firſt Company, Coronell of Dort.</head>
            <list>
               <item>MY Lord Haughton.</item>
               <item>Sir Walter Erle.</item>
               <item>Sir Roger Bartu.</item>
               <item>Sir Henry Hungate.</item>
               <item>Sariant Maior Groue.</item>
               <item>Captaine Thelwall.</item>
               <item>Captaine Wyborowe.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Price.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Pomroy.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Canſor.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Deemae.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Kettleby.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Luttrell.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Hammon.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Weynd.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Holman.</item>
               <item>Enſige Grimes.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Goldwel.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Hudſon.</item>
               <item>Mr: Winwood.</item>
               <item>Mr: Grifford.</item>
               <item>Mr: Byron.</item>
               <item>Mr: Thyne.</item>
               <item>Mr: Brigman.</item>
               <item>Mr: Fariefax.</item>
               <item>Mr: Hotham.</item>
               <item>Mr: Stone.</item>
               <item>Mr: Pellard.</item>
               <item>Mr: Bruſter.</item>
               <item>Mr: Knevet.</item>
               <item>Mr: Langford.</item>
               <item>Mr: Wayeman.</item>
               <item>Mr: Abſley.</item>
               <item>Mr: Rolt.</item>
               <item>Mr: Knasborow.</item>
               <item>Mr: Caue.</item>
               <item>Mr: Williams.</item>
               <item>Mr: Powel.</item>
               <item>Mr: Horner.</item>
               <item>Mr: Veyne.</item>
               <item>Mr: Wright.</item>
               <item>Mr: Baſſet.</item>
               <item>Mr: Berry.</item>
               <item>Mr. Prat.</item>
               <item>Mr: Bonnington</item>
               <item>Mr: Bradſhaw.</item>
               <item>Mr: Greene.</item>
               <item>Mr: Langdon.</item>
               <item>Mr: Hooe.</item>
               <item>Mr: Anſell.</item>
               <item>Mr: Hangerford.</item>
               <item>Mr: Crewell.</item>
               <item>Mr: Wilmore.</item>
               <item>Mr: Cullum.</item>
               <item>Mr: Eſſex.</item>
               <item>Mr: Mildmay.</item>
               <item>Mr: Polley.</item>
               <item>Mr: Maddocks.</item>
               <item>Mr: Humfreys.</item>
               <item>Mr: Ellis.</item>
               <item>Mr: Banberie.</item>
               <item>Mr: Garling.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Of my Lord Generall Vere his ſecond Company of Schoonhoven.</head>
               <item>Captaine Franciſco de Valrey.</item>
               <item>Captaine Straſly.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Tumour.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Quarles.</item>
               <item>Cornet Harbart.</item>
               <item>Mr: Wrengham.</item>
               <item>Mr: Bammham.</item>
               <item>Mr: Weldon.</item>
               <item>Mr: Norman.</item>
               <item>Mr: Sprye.</item>
               <item>Mr: Slippon.</item>
               <item>Mr: Coope.</item>
               <item>Mr: Harecourt.</item>
               <item>Mr: Maycote.</item>
               <item>Mr: White.</item>
               <item>Mr: Hearle.</item>
               <item>Mr: Inglot.</item>
               <item>Mr: Browne.</item>
               <item>Mr: Copley.</item>
               <item>Mr: Brimingham.</item>
               <item>Mr: Rolt.</item>
               <item>Mr: Guyn.</item>
               <item>Mr: Chitwood.</item>
               <item>Mr: Knightly.</item>
               <item>Mr: Sanderſon.</item>
               <item>Mr: Harmon.</item>
               <item>Mr: Sedgwicks.</item>
               <item>Mr: Wittington.</item>
               <item>Mr: Lee.</item>
               <item>M: Throgmotton.</item>
               <item>Mr: Nancy.</item>
               <item>Mr: King.</item>
               <item>Mr: Williams.</item>
               <item>Mr: Black.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Volunteirs of my Lord Generall Cieils Company, Vicount of Wimbleton.</head>
               <item>Leames Lord of Doncaſter.</item>
               <item>Boſwell Lord Peelding.</item>
               <item>William Lord Grauen.</item>
               <item>Sr: Thomas Glemman</item>
               <item>Captaine Henry Tyllie.</item>
               <item>Captaine Butler.</item>
               <item>Captaine Lucan.</item>
               <item>Sariant Maior Boules.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:22709:3"/>
               <item>Lieutenant Froeman.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Caſwell.</item>
               <item>Mr: Cicill.</item>
               <item>Mr: Whitepole.</item>
               <item>Mr: Clyford.</item>
               <item>Mr: Tate.</item>
               <item>Mr: Butler.</item>
               <item>M: Symon.</item>
               <item>Mr: Itby.</item>
               <item>Mr: Cheyncy.</item>
               <item>Mr: Broadbanke.</item>
               <item>Mr: Courtney.</item>
               <item>Mr: Downes.</item>
               <item>Mr: Footeman.</item>
               <item>Mr: Flood.</item>
               <item>Mr: Iohn Tate.</item>
               <item>Mr: Bois.</item>
               <item>Mr: Stuckling.</item>
               <item>Mr: Flemming.</item>
               <item>Mr: Rice Powell.</item>
               <item>Mr: Haughton.</item>
               <item>Mr: Hipſley.</item>
               <item>Mr: Appleyard.</item>
               <item>Mr: Ridley.</item>
               <item>Mr: Vackell.</item>
               <item>Mr: Solwin.</item>
               <item>Mr: Danniel.</item>
               <item>Mr: Colpher.</item>
               <item>Mr: Smith.</item>
               <item>Mr: Legg.</item>
               <item>Mr: Moynes.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Volunteirs &amp; Gentlemen of Generall Morgans Company.</head>
               <item>Sr: Thomas Bland.</item>
               <item>Sr: Shefeld Calpham.</item>
               <item>Sr: Iohn Coſling.</item>
               <item>Mr: Fowler.</item>
               <item>Mr: Mumford.</item>
               <item>Mr: Io: Withers.</item>
               <item>Mr: William Withers.</item>
               <item>Mr: Iſaack Abſley.</item>
               <item>Mr: Henry Abſley.</item>
               <item>Mr: Morgan.</item>
               <item>Mr: Tiffin.</item>
               <item>Mr: Elcott.</item>
               <item>Mr: Caruis.</item>
               <item>Mr: Reade.</item>
               <item>Mr: Andrewes.</item>
               <item>Mr: Booth.</item>
               <item>Mr: Merrick.</item>
               <item>Mr: Martin.</item>
               <item>Mr: Adam.</item>
               <item>Mr: Worly.</item>
               <item>Mr: Iohn Aſhley.</item>
               <item>Mr: Williams.</item>
               <item>Mr: Turner.</item>
               <item>Mr: Warret</item>
               <item>Mr: Garvis Wood</item>
               <item>Mr: Marſhall.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Volunteirs and Gentlemen of Coronell Harwoods Company.</head>
               <item>Captaine Perkins.</item>
               <item>Captaine Boules.</item>
               <item>Captaine Lowe.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Smith.</item>
               <item>Lieutenant Gamiſh.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Dolman.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Mariſon.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Hering.</item>
               <item>Mr: Lucas.</item>
               <item>Enſigne Byron.</item>
               <item>Mr: Muſchamp.</item>
               <item>Mr: Snelling.</item>
               <item>Mr: Browne.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Gentlemen of quality.</head>
               <item>Mr: Crofts.</item>
               <item>Mr: Gorges.</item>
               <item>Mr: Saint Iohn</item>
               <item>Mr: Bareford.</item>
               <item>Mr: Digby.</item>
               <item>Mr: Moſſe.</item>
               <item>Mr: Gilby.</item>
               <item>Mr: Lehunt,</item>
               <item>Mr: Waller.</item>
               <item>Mr: Ieffryes.</item>
               <item>Mr: Fleetewood.</item>
               <item>Mr: Killegrey.</item>
               <item>Mr: Lambart.</item>
               <item>Mr: Knightly.</item>
               <item>Lr: Bagſhot.</item>
               <item>Mr: Yonge.</item>
               <item>Mr: Frith.</item>
               <item>Mr: Boulton.</item>
               <item>Mr. Stewtly.</item>
               <item>Mr. Keckwich.</item>
               <item>Mr. Bendiſh.</item>
               <item>Mr: Roe.</item>
               <item>Mr: Raſſell.</item>
               <item>Mr: Carter.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Volunteirs and Gentlemen of Sr. Edward Veres Company deceaſed.</head>
               <item>Lieu. Harewood. Lieu. Turbot.</item>
               <item>M: Marſhan. M: Mando. M: Gallope.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Captaine John Cromwels Company.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr: Harry Cromwell.</item>
               <item>Mr: Rocheſter Karre.</item>
               <item>Officers and Souldiers ſlayne before the BUSSE. Of French.</item>
               <item>The Baron of Courtemer, and 8. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines more. Of the Dutch.</item>
               <item>Coronell Fama. Monſieur Grenue.</item>
               <item>Captaine Omkaes, and Capt. Hatton. Of Engliſh.</item>
               <item>Sir Edward Vere Lieut. Colonell.</item>
               <item>Capt. Roes Lieut. and Capt-Byroues. Of Scotch.</item>
               <item>Capt. Ramſey, Lieut. Huns, my Lord of Buckcloughs Enſigne. Of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions according to the lift giuen vp, about 1600.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:22709:3"/>
            <head>A SHORT DESCRIPTION OR Hiſtoricall Relation of the famous Siege of the BVSSE. And ſuch things as paſſed there, as well within as without the Citie. <hi>Vnder the commande of the</hi> Moſt Illuſtrious PRINCE OF ORENGE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE High and Mightie Lordes the States Generall, with the moſt Illuſtrious Prince of Orenge, taking nothing more to harte then the Proſperitie of theſe Free Vnyted Provinces, and the good Inhabitants in the ſame, had ſeuerall aſſemblies with the Prins of Orenge, conſulting howe to take in hand and haue in readineſſe whatſoeuer ſhould be needfull and fitting for a Famous Siege, and ſo reſolved to beſiege the citie called the Buſſe, but before wee wil ſpeake further of this Siege, wee ſhall firſt informe you of the ſcituation, Antiquitye, power and Renowne of this place.</p>
            <p>This place where the Buſſe is nowe ſcituated, hath beene formerly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the generall opinion of all men, a Wood or Parke where the Duke of Braband did vſe to hunte, and for this purpoſe himſelfe did cauſe a cottage or ſmall dwelling place, to be built there for his Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Houndes. But by reaſon the ſame place was verie comodious and had running ſtreames of freſh Water through it, many people of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Townes did meete there on Market dayes to trade with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And ſome of them built a few houſes there for to entertaine and lodge people, and others for to haue there comodities allwayes in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: But the Burgers of Heuſden envyeing theire good, did deſtroye them twyſe. Neuertheleſſe thoſe people complayning to the Duke of the wrongs done vnto them, he did graunte them to environ themſelues with Walles and Moates: After which this place did greatlie increaſe as well of trade as of people, yea manie ſtrangers came to liue there, and proſpered well, inſomuch that the Duke made it the fourth chiefe Citie in Braband, yet retayning the name of's Hertogenbos, which by in inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation is the Dukes-Wood, but commonly being called the BUSSE. And ſo this Citie builded a Townehouſe, a Court to entertayne the Duke, likewiſe many Churches, and in theſe latter times exceeding manie Monaſtaries. And in the yeere of our Lord 1380. the foundation of the greate Church called Sainct Iohns Church was layde.</p>
            <p>Alſo in thoſe times the Cittie was enlarged and made greater, and newe Walles moates and Bolwarkes, and foure ſeuerall gates made to it, vnder the commande of this citie at preſent doth belong Kempenlande, Peellande, Maſelande, and the Lande of Ooſterwyke, in which Landes are ſcituate foure chiefe Townes as Helmont, Eyndhoven, Megen and the Grave, beſides three ſcore and twelue Villages, wherein are one hundred and one Pariſh churches: Through this citie of the Buſſe run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a faire Ryver called the Dieſe, it lyeth 2. leagues from the Ryver
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22709:4"/> called the Maſe, 3. leagues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Heuſden, and 12. leages fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Anwerpe. This citie is marveillous ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g by reaso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lande which lyeth rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de about it, being verie lowe meddowes which almoſt continually are overwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with water, eſpecially in the Winter ſeaſon, inſomuch that none can aſſaulte it from without. Beſides the ſtrong Fortification of this citie of high Bulwarkes, very broad Moates, Hornworkes, halfe Moones. It was ſtrengthened with three greate and very ſtrong Fortreſſes or Sconces, twoo of them neare the Vuchter gate, where ſome high grounde lyeth. The greater and outwardmoſt is called the Fort Iſabella. The leſſer which lyeth betweene that and the citie is called Sainct Antonio. And the other which lyeth on the Eaſtſide of the citie in a Morrace, is called the Petler-Sconce. Thus much touching the deſcribing of the citie to you.</p>
            <p>Nowe to returne to this preſent Siege, the Prins of Orenge by order of the Lordes the States Generall, did beginne very timely in the yeere ſente vp ſome ſhipping with Ordinance, Amunition and other warrelike neceſſaries to Nimmegen, and to the Sconce of's Gravenweert. After this aboute the midſt of Aprill Anno 1629. the Prins cauſed the moſt parte of his Forces to be rayſed out of theire Garriſons, taking theire Rendevous towardes the ſaid Sconce: And ſo with a greate Reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and courage on the 24. of Aprill early in the morning at 6. of the clocke, his Eccellence departed out of the Hage with a braue Trayne of Valliant Commanders and Officers, and went directly for Utrick, from thence for Arnhem, and ſo for's Gravenweert. Where his Eccellence finding his Troopes in readineſſe, inſtantly departed and marched to the Mokerheath, and there the whole Army ſtood in Battell the 28. of Aprill, and quartered that night vnder the Heavens Canopy. The next morning at the breake of daye they marched forward to the citie called the Grave over the Bridge, and ſo directly towardes the BVSSE, where a Troope of Horſe came that ſame euening. And the next daye which was the 30. of April they viewed the Citie, and in the afternoone aboute three a clock his Eccellentie came thither with his whole Armye, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quartering himſelfe with 134. Companies at Vucht, a Village very neere to the twoo greate Sconces called Iſabella and Anthonio, and tooke his owne lodging in a faire ould building called Heymſhouſe. The other chiefe Quarters his Excellence ordered in this manner. Counte Ernſt at Hintem with 50. Companies, Counte William of Naſſau, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Heuſden at Orten with 32. Companies. The Lorde of Brederode aboute the Petteler-Sconce with 26. Companies, and the Count of Solms at Engelen, neere Crevecoeur, for the ſafetie of our Victuall and Amunition Shipping which laye there.</p>
            <p>And one the 11. of Maye Monſ. Pinſen came thither with 23. Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and tooke his Quarter at Deuteren. In the meane time all the Quarters being layd out, and every Regiment and Companye hauing theire ground giuen them: His Excell. cauſed certaine thouſandes of Huſbandemen to come out of the Betuw, the Tieler and Bommeler-Weerd, and other places to the campe, which with the helpe of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers did in few dayes entrench euery Quarter: and being defenſible, as ſo many bees to theire hiues, ſo each Souldier brings ſome thing to make himſelfe a Hutt. This being done his Excellence rides about to view the ground: The Line of circumvallation being nigh 30. Engliſh Miles in circuit. The Siege running thus, from the right ſide of the Dam, (where a Riuer called the Dommel was ſtopt) it ran along by Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Cicills Regiment, and ſo to Coronell Harwords, from thence to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22709:4"/> the French and Walloones, and along the Heath to the ſtone Gallowes. Then a long to Deuteren, from thence to the Buſſe-Sloate, and ſo along the men of warre to Engelen and Crevecoeur, and from thence on the other ſide of the Riuer called the Dieſe downe to Orten, from thence to Hintem, where Count Ernſt his Quarter laye, and ſo forward to Coud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water and to the Lord of Brederods Quarter, and thence along the Uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frouws Sconce and Berkel-Sconce to the Dam, where the out Line met againe.</p>
            <p>The Governor of the BVSSE called Grobbendoncq, hearing that our Army came marching towardes the Citie, and ſeeing our Horſemen making a bravado, in compaſſing and viewing thereof, could not beleeue or be perſwaded that it was intended to beſiege him, but that the plott was layd to beſiege Breda. Yea hee ſaid playnlie that he did thinke the Prins was not ſo vnwiſe for to beginne ſuch a fooliſh acte. But preſently after perceiuing that he ſetled his Quarters, and his Army approching towardes the Citie and to annoye it, hee began to ponder his owne negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that he had not provyded the Citie ſufficiently of Men, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Gunpowther, although a little before he could haue had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thouſand weight of powther from Luyke, which for the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe of monnie tooke noe effect. This newes comming to Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and other places in Braband, ſome ſet very light by it, eſteeming this Citie to bee invincible, but others conſidering theire vnpreparedneſſe and wante of men and monnie, were much amaſed.</p>
            <p>The Archducheſſe ſent one Poſt after another for Spayne, cauſed her chiefe Commanders of warre to aſſemble, and beganne to laye theire witts togeather howe to rayſe monnies, for the paye of theire Souldiers, that ſo they might gett them in feelde. Grobbendoncq wrote in all haſt for more men and powther, and that the Archducheſſe would vſe ſome ſpeedie meanes to releeue the Citie, ſome of the Enemies cheefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders, when they heard of this (as I am credibly informed) ſayd ſmylinglie, that Grobbendoncq was one of thoſe ſtout and valliant men, which did not feare the Divel himſelfe, yea ſcoffed at him, and as it were deſyred to ſee hem. As this Governor did often wiſh that the Prins would come and viſit him, but when he ſawe him indeed, he was as ſore affrayde as the reſt, and deſyred ſooneſt to be rid of him.</p>
            <p>His Excellence the firſt daye of Maye ſuffered divers Women, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Nunnes &amp; Maydſervantes to departe out of the Citie. The Troo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of Horſmen, which laye in Garniſon within the Citie, thought alſo to paſſe out of the Citie, without anie conſent of the Prins, but were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to returne in the Towne againe. Betweene the 4. and 5. of Maye in the night, there ſlipt into the Towne ſome 800. Men, which came from Breda by the waye of Vlymen and along Deuteren, (where Monſieur Pinſens Quarters was afterward) and from thence wading vp to the Armepitts in the water got into Sainct Iohns gate. By reaſon whereof his Excellence did cauſe a Dyke to be made from the Vuchterheath to Pinſens Quarter, over the drownedland by Grobbendoncks Koy, and likewiſe along the Buſſe-Sloate, as farre as to Engelen, wrought all by Peſants, which brought earth and Sande thither in boates, with twigs of trees or bruſh to laye vnder and betwixt the earth, that the water might not waſh it awaye. And ſo the whole Siege was compaſſed and ſhutt in 8. or 10. dayes.</p>
            <p>Betweene the 11. and 12. of Maye Count Ernſt did approche in his Quarter as farre as is noted in the Mappe from A to B, and there made a Corps de guarde, and bargayned with his Workemen to make him a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22709:5"/> Batterie there of ſixe peeces of ordinance, which Batterie within tenne or twelue dayes after was made, being very neere within Muſket ſhott of the Towne.</p>
            <p>And by reaſon the water encreaſed there could be noe neerer appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches made at that time, becauſe all the ground towardes the Citie ſtood blanke vnder water, to which ende the Enemy in the Citie cut aſunder the Cadyke, going towardes the Orterdyke, noted with the letter D.</p>
            <p>The 14. daye of Maye our men brought 40. flat Turfe Ships in the Camp to make Bridges. The 15. the enemie ſallied forth of the Petler vpon the Lord of Brederoods Quarter, but were ſoone drouen backe againe. The 16. they of Towne ſallied forth of the Towne in boates vpon Count Ernſt his Quarter, but were faine to retraict, not ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting any thing againſt vs. Aboute the 20. we began to make an out Line betwixt Engelen and Crevecoeur, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſafety of our Horſe, and all the Lines hauing twoo ſteps: The bottome thereof being aboute 16. foote, and the top 6. foote broade. And by the Vlymer-Bridge his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence cauſed a Sconce to be made againſt the ſtragling Souldiers of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, which was thought invincible. The 22. Count William cauſed ſome Canon ſhot to be made into the Towne of 6. and 7. pound bullets, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes hauing perfected a Batterie, did continue in ſhooting with twoo halfe Cannons, which ſent in bullets of 24. pound, and a little peece which ſhot 6. pound.</p>
            <p>The 23. a Poſt ventured to get into the Towne, but being deſcryed &amp; followed was drownde by the waye, but neuertheleſſe our people got him dead, and brought his ſecrett Letters to the Prince.</p>
            <p>The Outline of the Siege being thus finiſhed and made defencible, then the Engliſh and French, which were in his Excellencies Quarter, broake ground, and each Nation ſtriuing for his honour made towardes the Towne, to wit the French towardes the greate Sconce Iſabella, with their Ingeners Monſ. Porcibal and his Sonne, and the Engliſh towardes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="A"/> the leſſer and farther Sconce, called Sainct Antony, with theire Ingeners Ian de Bos and Maſter Humphry.</p>
            <p>The 28. Count Ernſt commaunded to make ſhott into the Citie, with three halfe Cannons; and ſuddenly after his Batterie being finiſhed, did continue ſhooting with twoo halfe Cannons, which ſhot Bullets of 24. pound, and afterwardes with three peeces more of 12. pound ſhott.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="B"/> The ſame daye in the night ſome 30. or 40. Muſkettiers ſallied forth of the greate Sconce Iſabella, and did diſcharge vnder the Ordinance of our Carabins, and ſo retraicted, not doeing any thing elſe.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="C"/> The 29. Porcival made a Line, which they of the greate Sconce broke in peeces, and ſo was left.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye Counte William cauſed ſhot to be made into the Towne from a ſecond Batterie, with three peeces of Ordinance, which carryed Bullets of 24. pound, and with other three peeces of 12. pound, and his firſt Batterie with three peeces of 6. pound, and one of 3. pound, alſo continuing.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="D"/> The 30. came forth of the greate Sconce Iſabella 40. Muſkettiers, vnto our approches, and diſcharging theire firelockes mayming ſome of our men returned againe.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye thoſe of the little Sconce ſallied forth, and killed an Engliſh Lieftenante and his man, with Muſket ſhort hurting another Souldier, and ſo were drouen in againe.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Iune in the night they of the Towne fyred vpon the top of the Church ſteeple three times, pulling vp the fire euery time thriſe: the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22709:5"/> French ſeeing this fell vpon ſome Workes, which thoſe of the greate Sconce had made, chaſing them out of theire Workes and got manie ſhouelles, armes and other implements.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh in the meane time making Waye and Paſſage towardes the little Sconce, drawing neerer and neerer.</p>
            <p>And by reaſon the water began to diminiſh &amp; fall at this time, Count Ernſt went forwarde with his approches, and made the twoo Lines, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with C and E, and made a Corps de guarde vpon F, in the Hinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-Waye.</p>
            <p>This Corps de guarde was finiſhed in fewe dayes after, being made Canon proofe, and guarded with Palliſadoes.</p>
            <p>The ſame time the French wonne the Line of the greate Sconce, which broke our Line which was made the 29. of Maye. At that time were ſlaine a Leeftenant and a Volantarie, likewiſe Monſieur de Vitre was ſhot in his ſhoulder and thigh, neere to the Conterſcharpe of the greate Sconce.</p>
            <p>Betweene the ſecond and third daye, Count Ernſt approched with the Lines, which are marked G, H, I, to ſome ſmall millhills K, and there made a Corps de guarde, which afterwardes was changed and made a Batterie for twoo halfe Cannons.</p>
            <p>On Whitſonday the 3. of Iune the French beganne to ſhoote with 6. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="F"/> peeces of 24. pound Bullets, from a Batterie which was made in the Line of Communication, paſſing from the Engliſh Workes to the French, for the aſſiſtance of on another if need were.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye at night they of the Towne drewe vp fire againe in the greate Church ſteeple.</p>
            <p>The 6. and 7. of Iune, And whereas the approaches and Corps de gardes in Counte Ernſt his Quarter daylie were furthered, ſo he approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched from the ſaid Millhills along the Line L, and at M made a Corps de garde, from whence his men went to the letter N, the Line of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication along the Kadyke to the Quarter of Counte William. And the ſame night approached to the Stonebridge in the Hintemer-Way to the letter O, and the 7. they began to ſap ouer that Bridge, and the night following made the Corps de garde, which is marked with the letter P. And the dayes following they did ſap towardes the Horneworke, at the Hintemer-end along the little Waye on both ſides thereof, becauſe the Lande laye vnder Water. Inſomuch that his Grace bargayned to make a Batterie there the 14. of Iune, for 3. peeces of Ordinance, at the letter Q. and afterwardes another Batterie of 2. peeces at the letter R.</p>
            <p>The 8. a French Captaine, called Monſieur de Vittenval, was ſhot in the Trenches, looking betweene twoo Cannon Baſkets, and his Lieften<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante ſucceeded in his place.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye the French began to make Cannon ſhot of 24. pound vpon the Horneworke of the greate Sconce.</p>
            <p>The 9. His Excellentie cauſed aboue 140. Canno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhot to be made vpon the little Sconce and into the Citie from the greate Batterie. And the ſame daye ſome Souldiers came forth of the Towne towardes Pinſens Quarter to take ſome Horſe and Workemen, but were drouen backe againe.</p>
            <p>Counte Ernſt at this time was adviſed by his Ingener Matthijs van Voord, to make a greate Gallerie directly vpon the Citie from the letter N. betweene the Hintemer-end and the Orter Bulwarke, which ſhould be made in this manner. The plaine thereof ſhould be a foote heigth aboue water, and 12. foote broad betweene the Walles thereof on both
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22709:6"/> ſides, which Walles ſhould be Cannon proofe. And at euery 8. or 10. foote length a Travers to be made alſo Cannon proofe. Which his Excellentie and Count Ernſt, with the States Committies approoved of: And ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly order was giuen that it ſhould be made. To this end the twoo Batteries marked S and T, were put forth to be made, each of them for eight peeces of Ordinance. The Wings or Hinderparte thereof cloſing togeather, and hauing on the ſides Corps de guardes, for the ſafetie of the Batteries, and ſo this greate Gallerie was begunne the 8. of Iuly by theſe Ingeners Matthijs van Voord and Iames Slip.</p>
            <p>And by reaſon the Place where this greate Gallerie was to be made was alltogeather a Morrace, which was overflowne with Water at ſome places a mans heigth, wee were faine to fill the Waye as we worked for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with bruſh and earth, which was brought thither from afarre of in Cartes. And for the more ſecuritie of this Gallerie, there were made the Batteries V and W.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye at night ſix Frenchmen went in Armour of Muſket proofe, to viewe the Conterſcharfe of the Horneworke belonging to the greate Sconce, but never a ſhot was made at them.</p>
            <p>The ſame night the French advanced theire workes to the Conter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcharfe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="H"/> of the Horneworke, where they began to mine, but ſtopped it againe.</p>
            <p>The 11. came into Count Ernſts Quarter eleauen Companies more of Scotſh.</p>
            <p>This daye the Engliſh began to make Cannonſhot of 24. pound at the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> little Sconce, from a Batterie that had twoo peeces, which ſhot at the Sconce gate.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="K"/> The ſame daye the French made ſhot from a Batterie, which they made vpon the Conterſcharfe of the Horneworke.</p>
            <p>Dito Monſieur de Candale came into the Quarter and had the Watch in the Trenches.</p>
            <p>The 14. the Engliſh began to ſhoote Granadoes out of 2. Morters into the greate Sconce Iſabella, and the little Sconce Sainct Antony, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="L"/> one fell into the Powther Roome of the greate Sconce, and with a wondrous greate Noyſe like a Thunder clap threwe as it were whole Houſes in the Ayre, to the admiration of diuers.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye his Excellentie and the States went vpon the Batterie, and ſent ſome Granadoes into the little Sconce, which made parte of the Walles to flie vp, that wee could hardlie ſee the Sconce for Duſt and Smoake.</p>
            <p>The laſt night they in the Towne drewe vp fire againe in the Church ſteeple.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye Count Ernſt went forwarde with his ſap along the ſmale Waye towardes the Hintemer-end, rayſing the paſſage with Bruſh and earth; and advanced ſo much that the 19. the Corps de guarde Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero 1. and vpon the 28. the Corps de guarde Numer. 2. were made. And to advance the workes of the mayne Gallerie at Numer. 3. and 4. twoo Batteries were made each of one peece of Ordinance.</p>
            <p>The 15. His Excell. commaunded to let the Water, which was ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at the Dommel, to runne rounde about his Quarter: And the ſame daye the Engliſh ſent ſix Granadoes into the twoo Sconces, whereof twoo made a fearefull ſtirre among them, &amp; threw ſome of theire Hutts over the Walles. Forcing the Enemye to ſaue themſelues in the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes, vntill the Granadoes had done theire operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wee in the meane time playeing vpon them with Cannon and Muſket ſhot as faſt as wee coulde.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:22709:6"/>
            <p>The 16. in the night the Enemie ſallied forth of the Hintemer-gate, and beate the Scotſh out of theire Trenches: as likewiſe thoſe of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="M"/> greate Sconce in number ſome 50. or 60. Men came out with Treſhing cudgels, Piſtolls and Clubs, and beate the French out of theire Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and ſlewe ſome of the Engliſh, which were employed there in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the French approches.</p>
            <p>The ſame night the Engliſh ſent three Granadoes into the little Sconce, and did greate endeavour to fill the moate of the halfe Moone with Bruſh and earth, but they of the Sconce threw forth hookes and pulled out our Bruſh ſometimes as faſt as we did put it in, and caſt out firebrandes and Handegranadoes to burne it, ſo that wee had hot worke to prevaile with them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe they of the greate Sconce threw forth Handegranadoes and Firebrandes to breake and burne the Gallerie, which the French began to make towardes the Horneworke, but nevertheleſſe they got vp that night three poſts or ioynts of theire Gallerie.</p>
            <p>The 17. the Engliſh were mynded to haue made an aſſaulte vpon the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="N"/> halfe Moone, being they had made a paſſage over the moate, but the Captaine of the Watch being hurte it was deferred.</p>
            <p>The 18. the French began to make a Gallerie directlie vpon the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlewing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="O"/> of the Horneworke.</p>
            <p>The 19. the Engliſh began to make a Gallerie towardes the halfe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="P"/> Moone of the little Sconce, &amp; the 20. they worked forwarde with theire Gallerie by cleere dayelight, and ſent eight Granadoes into it, which made the Enemye call vpon the name of the Ladye Mary moſt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullie and fled into theire Conterſcharfes to ſave themſelves. The night following they drewe vp fire in theire high ſteeple againe.</p>
            <p>The 21. were ſent 8. Granadoes more into the little Sconſe, with many Cannonſhot everie daye and inſtant.</p>
            <p>The 20. the French began a ſecond Gallerie on the right hand of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Q"/> firſt.</p>
            <p>And the ſame daye the French broake a myne into the Horneworke. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="R"/> 
            </p>
            <p>The 21. the Engliſh broake a myne into the halfe Moone of the little <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="S"/> Sconce. And began to make a ſecond Gallerie on the right hand of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="T"/> firſt.</p>
            <p>The 22. in the night the Engliſh went couragiouſly forwarde with theire Gallerie, but they of the Sconce ſallied forth and ſet it on fyre. The Engliſh nevertheleſſe watching an oppurtunity, ſuddenlie fell vpon the Enemie, inſomuch that they had noe time to ſeeke and returne the ſame waye which they came forth. And ſo divers of them being enforced to make ſpeed or to be put to the ſworde leaped into the moate and there were drowned.</p>
            <p>The ſame night the Engliſh ſet fyre on theire myne and made an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulte vpon each ſide of the halfe Moone, but the myne operating con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theire expectation, they beganne another myne and went for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with theire Galleries.</p>
            <p>The French alſo gave fire to a myne but effected little.</p>
            <p>At this time Count Henry of Berck Muſtered his Army at Turnhout, being in number ſome 25000. Men foote and horſe.</p>
            <p>In the afternoone the French gave fire to twoo mynes more, but avay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not. The third made ſuch a breach into the Wall of the Horneworke, that wee could ſee the Enemie in it from top to toe. And ſo they ſhould have made an aſſaulte vpon them, but by reaſon the ſpringing of the myne caſt ſo much earth into the Mouth of the Gallerie, that they could
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22709:7"/> not goe forth of it, they were prevented and the breach ſuddenly ſtoppet againe.</p>
            <p>The 24. and 25. wee did effect little.</p>
            <p>The 26. there was a greate fire in three ſeverall places of te Siege, as namely in the Horſe Quarter, in the Engliſh Quarter and in Brederoes Quarter, it was ſuſpected to be villany of Traytors, but we could not finde them out.</p>
            <p>At this time Count Henry of Berch marching towardes vs, lodged his Forces at Sprang, Wallwyke, Druynen and Loon.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time the King of Bohemia came vnto the Siege, and went with his Excell. into the Trenches, and viewed our Approaches, Batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and other Workes.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> The 27. the French paſſed ouer the moate of the Conterſcharpe, and made Cannon ſhott from a Batterie on the right hand of the Gallerie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> and made on each ſide thereof a ſmall Batterie.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye Count Henry of Berch came with his Army to Vly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and appeared in our ſight at ſeuerall places with his Horſe, which went vp and downe to viewe our Outworkes. In the night they of the Towne cauſed an Alarme to be made, which made vs thinke that the Enemie would haue fallen vpon vs from without and within, but they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted nothing.</p>
            <p>The 28. Count Henry appeared with his Forces in the night neere the Hollands Dyke, and by our greate Sconces called the 3. Siſters, but we hauing ſent them ſome 10. or 12. Cannonſhot they retired backe: Our whole Army nevertheleſſe ſtanding in Battle all the night long.</p>
            <p>The 29. many of the Enemies Souldiers came into our Quarters, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playning of greate ſcarſitie, hunger and hardneſſe.</p>
            <p>The 30. the Enemye laye themſelues in Embuſcado neere the Uf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frou Sconce, and tooke diuers of Waggons and Waggonmen, which went forth for Bruſh. Likewiſe they tooke the Houſe of Heſop and Box<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, where we had ſome ſmall ſtrength of Souldiers, which they let paſſe with theire Armes and Baggagie into our Camp. In the morning came twoo of the Enemies Sloopes to the 3. Siſters and the Hollands Dyke, to take meaſure of the depth of the Water, which made our Army to riſe in Armes. Some more Souldiers of the Enemie comming to vs, reported that in theire Campe Cheeſe was ſould for 12. ſtiuers a pound, and a Pot of Beere for 6. ſtiuers: Inſomuch that the common Souldiers were all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt famiſhed for want of monnie and foode, which cauſed them to flee from them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Iuly Monſieur Fama was ſhot and dyed of it.</p>
            <p>The Enemye continually buzzing vp and downe, ſent ſome 4000. Horſe and foote with 800. firelockes, each hauing a leather bag of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to put them into the Towne, betweene the Petler Sconce and Count Ernſt Quarter, and brought along with them Spades, Fagots and Plankes to fall vpon a Horneworke of ours, not farre from Coudwater, but being diſcovered by our men in the night, which ſtood readie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue them, the Alarme being giuen; They were beate of ſome of them drowned, and others being ſhot and wounded, retreated and lefte ſome of theire powther baggs behinde them. This failling he had other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes by the helpe of twoo treacherous Peſants for the cutting of our Damme.</p>
            <p>The ſame night theſe Peſants as theire Guides brought his men along the little Dyke, which runnes from the Dam to Boxtel by the Boores Houſes, but they in the night diſcovered Generall Cicills Tents, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22709:7"/> were newly ſett vp, their harts miſgaue them, thinking we knew of their plot, and ſo retreated without attempting it, parte of a Companie onely hauing the guarde at the poinct vpon the Dyke, while the reſt of the Companies were drawne to the Line vpon the Heath, they might eaſilie haue effected it. Our Men in the morning diſcouering them as they marched towarde Count Henryes Quarter, the twoo halfe Cannons which laye vpon Cicills Batterie let fly at them, and ſlew ſome of them: But to preuent this the next daye his Excell. cauſed abundance of Palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadoes to be driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into the Dyke, and made a Batterie where they ſhould haue come one, and from thence to Berckel Sconce chayned boates to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather ouer the Water; ſetting watch in them by night, for the defence of the Damme.</p>
            <p>Count Henry of Berke being then quartered at Boxtel, Cromforde and Helforde, within an Engliſh mile and a halfe of our Line, wee were faine to make the nights our dayes, and the dayes our nights, expecting continually his comming vpon vs with maine Force, which oftentimes he attempted but to little effect, which laſted aboue three weekes togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vntill hee left vs. In the meane time the Companies of all Nations beſet the Line of Circumvallation, ſome twoo hundred paces diſtant one from another round about the Army: The Horſe ſtanding behind them in Battaile readie to receaue him. His Excellentie euery night about midnight goeing the grand Round to anſwere all Alarmes. The ſame night that he intended to put in theſe firelockes and their powther bags into the Towne, and to haue cut the Damme, and to haue let in a Sea of water vpon vs, which ranne rownde about our Quarters, returning from Vlymen with the groſſe of his Army, he diſcovered himſelfe betimes in the morning, aſſoone as it beganne to be light by the downes, and had layd an Embuſcado of Muſketteirs in a ditch by ſome trees, and behinde the downes he made a halte with his Horſe and foote, and ſends out firſt ſome 10. or 12. Horſe to entertaine a ſkermiſh with ſome of our Horſe, which ſtood readie in Armes without our Line vpon the Heath, hauing the Outguarde. The Trumpets ſounde a Charge, and our Canno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s roares from all the Batteries at the Enemye, and as the ſkermiſh enceaſed, ſo wee ſent them the more Bullets, which made divers of their Horſmen to turne vp theire heeles, wee ſeeing oftentimes leggs and Armes flie vp, and their Horſe roule over one anothers. At laſt there came three troope of Horſe, which changed Bullets with our Horſemen, and ſtill our Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance giuing fire among them, and our Horſe charging them towarde the foote of the downes, the fayned a retreate to drawe on our Horſe within their Embuſcado. Monſieur Mauue a French Captaine of a troope of Horſe, charging home his Horſe from the Embuſcado was ſlayne vnder him. The Enemy falls out againe with more Horſe and takes this French Captaine priſoner. The Duke of Bullen ſeing him thus engaged, chargeth with a troope or twoo for to reſcue him, and while twoo of the Enemyes men were a diſputing whoſe priſoner he ſhould be, our Horſe charges them againe, and drives them to a retreate, they not having time to carry their Priſonner away, to end the diſpute piſtole him, and ſo the Duke brought of his dead bodie. This ſkirmiſh during a while after, Count Henry marched awaye, and we to our Quarters.</p>
            <p>The 4. of Iuly in the night the Enemy came vpon our Army, intending to breake the ſtoppage of the Dommel, but were prevented and manie of them ſlayne. At this time ſome Peſants were taken, which had led the Enemy &amp; ſhewen them the way through the water howe to come vpon vs as they did ſeuerall times in the night. Whereof twoo were hanged in his Excell: Quarter.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:22709:8"/>
            <p>Having made this digreſſion, I returne againe to our Approaches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Engliſh came to the laying over of their firſt Gallerie. There the Captaine of his Excell: Guard got a dangerous ſhot in the forhead that he loſt his eye. Captaine Omkaes a worthy Ingener ſhewing his bodie too open was ſnapt of and ſlaine with a firelocke, and Captaine Clarke ſhot through both his legs, and hauing brought over their Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, they could not come to the moate of the little Sconce, before they had beaten the Enemie out of twoo Traverſes, and a point which came out of the Conterſcharfe in the forme of a halfe Moone on our right hand next the Dommel, at the entrance of the Gallerie: Over this firſt Water on the left hand they had a Batterie vpon which Coronell Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood was ſhot through his hat; The Lord of Oxford ſtanding by. The Gallerie being ouer they beganne to ſap and made a mine in the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes firſt Traverſe, that night which Sir Iacob Aſhley commanded in the Trenches deſirous of honour, he was appointed with ſome 60. Pikes and Muſketteirs to fall on after the Mine was ſprong; and Captaine Gouldwell as eldeſt Captaine to ſecond him with more Men before the Mine was blowne vp, he gaue the Enemy an Allarme to drawe them on towardes our Mine; and the Mine being ſprung ſet on with his Men and beate the Enemie to a retreate out of parte of theire Travers, our Men &amp; the Enemye giuing fire brauelie one to another a good while, but the Engliſh lyeing open to the Bulwarke of the little Sconce, and their other Traverſe, were faine to retreate againe into the Mouth of their Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. This Mine tooke not well, but ſprang rather backward then forward, and did more hurte to our Men then to the Enemye; yet from this earth which was caſt vp out of the Enemyes Travers they beganne to ſap for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, which the Enemye ſeeing at laſt they quitted it, and ſo became Maſters of it, and getting a little more elbowe roome they advanced for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the moate of the little Sconce, making Guardes, Batteries and Blindes, till they came to the very brinke of it, where they beganne a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Gallerie.</p>
            <p>The 7. of Iuly in the euening aboute eleauen a clocke, Monſieur Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, Leeftenante to Coronel Chattillon, commanding the French Trenches, they of the Conterſcharfe ſallied forth in number about 100. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Y"/> Men, and overcame by force of Armes twoo of our Corps de guardes, and mayntained them againſt vs for the ſpace of an houre, and then being forced to leaue them in the retreate; the Enſigne which commanded them was taken priſoner. In the meane time ſome 200. Men of the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neworke intended to ſallie forth, but being diſcouered returned backe againe.</p>
            <p>The 8. the Enemye blewe vp a Mine vpon the Engliſh, but did them noe harme.</p>
            <p>The 9. Monſ. Chattillons Companie hauing the guard in the French Approaches, fell vpon the Horneworke of the greate Sconce, and founde but 7. or 8. Men in it, which did not diſpute the matter long &amp; quitted it and retired to their Conterſcharfe, where on their right hand they cut it off, and made a ſmall Travers in it, whence they gaue fire with their Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketteirs and firelockes vpon them. But the French hauing put their Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie ouer the moate of the Conterſcharfe, they came to the ſecond moate of the greate Sconce, where they likewiſe put over a Gallerie into the Faulſebray. On the left hand of their Gallerie, the Enemye had cut off their Faulcebray to hinder our Workemen and Miners by giuing fire from a ſmall Travers vpon them.</p>
            <p>The 11. his Excellencye cauſed an inwarde Line to be made towardes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22709:8"/> the Citie, beginning at Pinſens Quarter, and ſo paſſing by his Excellent. Quarter came to Brederoes Quarter, and went from thence to Count Ernſts Quarter, being fortified with manie Redouts, whereby thoſe of the Towne were prevented to come forth vnto our Quarters.</p>
            <p>The 12. Count Morris of Naſſau was made Coronel in ſteede of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Fama.</p>
            <p>The 14. his Excell: gaue order for the repayring of the Watermills <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Aa"/> neere the Dieſe, and appointed 21. Mathematicall Mills to be made there beſides, which drewe vp abundance of water from belowe, ſucking it vp with funnells, and caſting it vp diſmiſt it ſelfe vpon the higher Lande making a new currant.</p>
            <p>The Gallerie in Count Ernſts Quarter Numer. 5. was appointed to be made the 8. of Iuly, but not begonne before the 14. for want of earth, vpon which Gallerie the Enemy ſhot verie hotlie, both with Cannon and muſketts; inſomuch that manie of the Workemen in the Mouth of this Gallerie were ſlayne.</p>
            <p>The Gallerie being brought over, the Enemy retired in thoſe places which they had cut off, noted in the Mappe Numer. 8. &amp; 9. but in reſpect the Scotſh continually went forwarde with ſapping along the ſide of the Horneworke, the Enemy was forced likewiſe to leaue thoſe places.</p>
            <p>The 15. Count Henry of Berke rayſed his Army and departed from Boxtel, marching towardes the Graue, and paſſed the Maſe over the Moakerheath, but firſt ſent a Peſant to bring a Letter to the Gouvernor Grobbendonk in the Towne, which Peſant was taken in our Army vpon ſome ſuſpition and the Letter founde, and brought to his Excellentie. The tennor whereof was as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MY LORD.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Seeing it is vnpoſſible to overmaſter the Enemy in his Workes, with that ſtrength which I haue at preſent, in reſpect he hath faſtened himſelfe extraordinarily. I haue thought good to rayſe my Army and departe from hence, and to joyne my Forces with thoſe of the Emperours, which nowe are readie in Armes, and in greate number mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to Weſel, as well Horſe as Footemen, intending to take in hand ſome remarkable thing, whereby the Enemy ſhall be compelled to fight with vs, and that it pleaſing God to giue vs the Victorie therein, the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall be thereby releeued, you in the meane time keeping it yet for a while, which I thought fitting at preſent to giue you notice of. Praying when you haue receaued this, to drawe vp in the night a greate fire in the ſteeple of S. Iohns Church, ſtirring it oftentimes, and the next daye to let a greate ſmoke appeare aboue the ſteeple, whereby I maye knowe this Letter was deliuered you; and when this Meſſenger ſhall returne with your anſwere, that you make the like ſigne in the night following and with ſmoke the next daye in the meane time. I reſt</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>MY LORD</salute>
                     <signed>Your affected and faithfull Frend HENRY COUNT OF BERKE.</signed>
                     <dateline>From our Campe at Boxtel <date>the 16. of Iuly 1629.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>The Superſcription was thus, To My Lord, the Baron of Grobbendonk, Knight of the Order of S. Iames, Coronell of a Regiment of Walloons, and Governor of the BUSSE.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22709:9"/>
            <p>But this Letter falling into the handes of his Excellentie, he ſent it to the Lordes the States Generall of theſe Unyted Low Countrye Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, with his advyſe and counſell what he thought fitting to be done againſt the Enemyes plot, his Excellentie likewiſe ordered an Army of Foote and Horſe out of his Campe, vnder the commaund of Count Otto van Stierum, to followe Count Henry, and watch what he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; nevertheleſſe himſelfe continueing the Siege before the BUSSE.</p>
            <p>The 18. the Lord van Dieden, Governor of Emmerick, then comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the French Trenches, hauing blowne vp a Myne in the greate Sconce, which overwhelmed twoo of our men that ſtood too neere it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Bb"/> The French entered, &amp; finding noe reſiſtance, tooke the greate Sconce. There were founde in it 16. Hogſheads of Wyne, 24. Barrells of Beere, greate quantity of Bread and Porke, a Boy and a Dog, with a Sellar of Yſe to coole Wyne or Beere in the heate of the Summer.</p>
            <p>The 19. of Iuly in the morning about three a clocke, the Enemy like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Cc"/> quitted the little Sconce, wherein was founde ſeuerall Armes and Houſhouldſtuffe.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye Coronell Harwood commaunding the Engliſh Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, after he had taken the little Sconce, went forward and likewiſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Dd"/> beate the Enemye out of a Traverſe, which they had made without the Sconce, and ſo they fled to theire halfe Moone, which was 250. paces from thence towardes the Towne. The Engliſh and the French after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes releeued one another in approaching and ſapping towardes the Towne euerie fourth night, and the Dutch hauing the Watch after them one night. And ſo his Excellentie cauſed ſome Batteries to be made by <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ee"/> the little Sconce, which ſhot vpon the Tenaille, Vuchtergate and halfe Moone thereof; wee in the meane time ſapping forwardes towardes the Tenaille, which was the next thing that laye in our waye.</p>
            <p>The 20. Count Otto van Stirum departed out of our Camp with an Army of 1200. Horſe and 4000. foote to followe the Enemy.</p>
            <p>The 23. came newes to our Camp that Count Henry with his and the Emperours Forces, were got over the Ryver called the Yſell into the Veluw, which daunted vs much, being the Enemye could runne vp from thence without paſſing over any more Waters, even to the principall Cities of Hollande, as he did partlie, his deſſigne being thereby to make vs breake vp the Siege of the BUSSE, and to come to prevent his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding. But his Excell. ſeeing the Towne could not hould out long, ſent forth Count Ernſt with Coronell Harwood, and ſo many foote and Horſe as he could ſpare out of his Camp, to hinder the Enemys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming over the Ryne into the Betu, as he afterwardes (when he had brought his Forces into the Velu) did oftentimes attempt, which if he could haue effected, would haue beene greatlie to our diſadvantage.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ff"/> The 26. the Sergeant Major of the French, which then had the watch in the Trenches, brought a bridge of ruſhes over the moate of the halfe Moone, which laye before the Tenaille, and making a Rempart in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Gg"/> halfe Moone, the Enemye left it and fled to the Tenaille.</p>
            <p>The 28. the Enemye ſallied forth of the Towne in Boates, and tooke divers Priſoners, whereof ſome were Burgers, that were gone too neere the Towne to ſee ſtrange things.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye came into our Camp the Yong Prins of Denmarke with a Regiment of Dutch.</p>
            <p>The 3. of Auguſt a Bridge of ruſhes was brought over the moate of the Tenaille.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:22709:9"/>
            <p>The 4. Monſieur Douchant hauing the Watch in the Approaches <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Hh"/> aboute noone ſprong a Myne in the Tenaille, after he had layd twoo Ruſh-Bridges over the moate thereof, and about ſome 100. of the French went on verie furiouſlie into the breach which the myne had made, ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ii"/> it with halfe Pykes: But the Enemye reſiſted them verie ſtoutlie, and ſlew many being moſt of them Volontaries, and ſo put them backe by force, which Combate his Excellentie ſawe ſtanding vpon the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke of the little Sconce.</p>
            <p>The 6. of Auguſt Monſieur de Candale commanding the French <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Kk"/> Trenches, made a ſap on the right hand of the Tenaille, which did the Enemye much harme, afterwardes he cauſed a Corps de guarde to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Ll"/> made to make ſhot on the ſideway; and the daye after ſent them manye of Granadoes.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye Monſieur Pinſen made a Batterie verie neere the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, from whence he caſt them manie Granadoes.</p>
            <p>The 8. Monſieur Maurice Coronell of the Walloones hauing the watch in the Trenches, the Enemye left the Tenaille, after twoo Mynes were ſprong, the third being readie, and ſo was taken and a greate Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie made of it of nine halfe Cannons.</p>
            <p>On the 10. of Auguſt Grobbendonk in the night ſent forth twoo Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, apparrelled like Countriemen, with Letters to the Arch-Ducheſſe, each of them hauing a paire of Doves, which ſhould haue beene caſt vp and flie into the Towne with anſwer backe againe: But their hartes fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, and fearing to be taken by our Men in paſſing the Line and Watches: the one Souldier being more willing then the other, drew out his Knife and threatned to kill the other, if he would not goe along with him to the Prince, and ſo calling to our Centinells; the Guard receiued them in: the contents of the Letters were, that he could not hould out the Towne aboue three weekes longer, and the Burgers for the ſauing of their liues and goodes, and ſhunning of ſudden danger would force him to a compoſition, and therfore required releife within that time, or elſe it would goe verie hard with them, of all which the Prince made good vſe.</p>
            <p>To goe on the Tenaille being ours, we beganne a new ſap from the right point thereof towardes the Enemyes halfe Moone, without the Vuchter-Gate running the Approaches by oblique Lines, windings and turnings till wee came to the verie brinke of the Moate of the Towne, where the Dommell falleth into it, making the moate and it aboue 300. foote over, and euer as wee got ground ſo we advanced our Ordinance, made Batteries, Gards and Blinds for the ſafegard of our Men: there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Mm"/> the firſt entrance of our mayne Gallerie into the moate to be put ouer into the Bulwarke on the right hand of the Gate, on both ſides of this Gallerie there were made for the defence of it a ſmall Batterie of twoo halfe Cannon, which beate vpon the bricke foundation of the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke, and flankard our Gallerie on both ſides; the Ordinance likewiſe, which were planted vpon the Tenaille, playd vpon the Bulwarkes on each ſide of the Towne gate, to diſmount their Ordinance, which ſhot vpon the end of our Gallerie and of our Workemen, but the Enemyes Ordinance were ſo ſunke, that wee could not come at them. From vnder the ſaid Tenaille was alſo a planke Bridge layd over the Dommell, and a Blinde made to get into the Vuchter-end or bleach feelde: In this patch of ground were made Blindes and Batteries to diſmount the Enemyes Ordinance, which playd vpon our Galleries and Workemen, from the Bulwarke on the left hand of the Gate, and a peece which they had ſuuke
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22709:10"/> in their halfe Moone. In this Feelde alſo we began to laye over a ſecond Gallerie on the right face of the Bulwarke; but the Enemyes Ordinance from the Bulwarkes on the further ſide of the Gate ſhot through it 8. or 10. times, breaking ſome of the poſts aſunder, at the entrance of it into the moate, yet at the laſt our Batterie in that Feelde put them to ſilence, and an Engliſh Captaine an excellent Cannonnier diſmounted their halfe Cannon, that daye the Lord of Oxford had the Guarde after, which our Men working more ſafelie in both the Galleries.</p>
            <p>The 13. manye Granadoes were caſt into the Towne, which threw downe manie Houſes.</p>
            <p>The 15. of Auguſt in the night the Enemye had a Stratagem to cutt our Trench by the little Mill and Coudwater, betweene Count Ernſt and Brederoes Quarter, and ſo to haue let in the Water vpon our Approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; to put this into execution, Grobbendonk ſent out of the Towne ſome hundred and fiftie firelockes and ſpades, which ſtole in the night betweene the Petler-Sconce and Count Ernſts Quarter through the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Line, where it was not finiſhed and came to the little Windmill by our out Line; and there hauing layd an Embuſcado of ſome of their fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lockes in a ditch, and behinde ſome buſhes fell to worke apace to cut our Trench ſome 30. foote broad betweene the Horneworke, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douts vpon the Line, not farre from that place where Count Henry of Berks Men would haue attempted it before: But parte of Captaine Brogs Companie hauing the gard in a Redoubt next vnto them gaue fire, and the Alarme being giuen: Our Horſe, which had the gard in a Houſe not farre from thence, came vp to charge them, and giuing fire likewiſe from that Redoubt, they lefte their worke, and retreated backe to their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, leauing their Spades and a paire of ould Shoes behind them, and as they retreated gaue fire vpon our Horſe, and ſlew a Corporall and hurte twoo or three more: But by reaſon of the Morrace and the Ditches, our Horſemen could not come to charge them, neither durſt our foote leaue their Guardes: and ſo they retreated backe againe into the Towne, ſome twoo Engliſh mile where they fell a cutting. Surelie if they had ſtayd but one halfe quarter of an houre longer, or cut the gap not ſo broad, they had effected the buſines they came for, becauſe the Water was not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing three ynches lower then the top of the Trench, and ſo ſhould haue let in an Inundation of Water vpon vs.</p>
            <p>The 16. of Auguſt newes came to our Campe that the Enemie had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Amersford.</p>
            <p>The 17. Count William then commaunding the Quarter and Workes of Count Ernſt, cauſed twoo Mines to be blowne vp, which were made vnder the Horneworke of the Hintemergate, alſo made twoo aſſaults vpon the Enemie, but prevayled not.</p>
            <p>The 18. in the morning the Enemie ſallied forth of the Towne neere Pinſens Quarter, and robbed ſome of the Victualers and ſo departed: the night following the Leeftenant Coronell Sir Edward Vere had the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund in the Trenches. And on Sondaye his Excellence who oftentimes ventered his perſon very much, came downe to the Gallerie to ſee the Approaches, a little before the ſaid Leeftenante Coronell was relieued, hee went to ſhew the Prince the Workes and the Sap, the Companies being relieued, were drawne off as far as the little Sconce. The ſaid Leef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tennante Coronell Vere hauing ſhowen his Excellentie the Sap, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his leaue of him, walking off with Sir Thomas Conway, being a Tall man, came an vnhappie Muſketſhot through the Blind, and ſhot him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in his head, that it periſht his braynes: that night being brought to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22709:10"/> his Tent within ſome foure dayes afterwardes dyed, whoſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie vallour ſufficiencie &amp; compleat abilities for a Commander as they were well knowne, ſo was his loſſe exceedinglie lamented by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentie and the Chiefes of our Army. My Lord Generall Vere, my Lord of Oxford, many Captaines, Officers, Voluntaries and Gentlemen of quality, who had beene at his funerall in Bommell returning home that night.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh Regiment had the guard in the Approaches, and a civill worthy Gentleman of my Lords Companie of Dort, one M. Mollenax that bare the ſword of the ſaid Leeftenant Coronell before his corps, goeing to ſee the ſap, was the firſt that night which followed him the waye of all fleſh; my Lord Generall Vere beſtird himſelfe, had all his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Souldiers in readineſſe, that vpon the firſt occaſion, if the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie had either ſallied out vpon our Sappers or Workemen, or if they ſhould haue attempted the firing of the Gallerie, they might haue beate them in againe. Captaine Rookewood of my Lord Veres Regiment as eldeſt Captaine, executed my Lords commaund with valour and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had his Granado-Men at hand, and placed diuers Muſketteirs vpon all flanks to playe vpon the Enemie, and to keepe them vnder for ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon the end of our Gallerie and our Workemen, and now and then ſent them ſome Cannon Bullets, which ſhot vpon the topp of their Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke, and vpon their halfe Moone to keepe them vnder, ſometimes ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a Granado into the Towne, and throwing Handgranadoes amongſt them into their halfe Moone. Towardes midnight the Enemie likewiſe did caſt Handgranadoes vpon our Blind next to their halfe Moone and ſet fire on it, which brake out into a greate flame, but the vigilency of my Lord Vere was ſuch fearing, that the fire might take further hould, he gaue order that ſome Souldiers ſhould take ſhouells and ſpades from the Workemen, and caſt earth and water vpon it, which cauſed it to ſlake, and had twoo or three Granadoemen there, which paid them with theire owne coine, but ſure it was good that the Wind blew Southweſt, for had the Wind blewe Northweſt and had blowne ſtiff, as it did, it had not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie endangered the firing of all our Blindes, but alſo our Gallerie, which would haue hindered our Approaches and caſt vs a greate deale behinde hand. And ſo this daye and night following the Gallerie and Workes were well advanced. This daye Sir Harry Hungate got a marke of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by a Bullet, which ſhot him thorow his buffe Ierkin, and grazed vpon his fleſh.</p>
            <p>Before our Regiment had the Watch againe in the Approaches the Gallerie was well advanced, and they got about three Poſts night and daye, it was then my Lord of Oxfords turne to commaund, who was made Leeftenante Coronell in Sir Edwarde Veres place deceaſed. The Bridge being layd ouer the Ditch of the Enemies halfe Moone. The Engliſh began to ſap, and lodged in the left corner of it, becauſe of the Trees that laye a croſſe in it. This night there was diſcouered an engine vpon a floate from the furtheſt parte of their halfe Moone by the moate, which wee preſuppoſed they had prepared for the firing of our Gallerie. To prevent this my Lord of Oxford got a Sloope, which was brought about towards our Gallerie, that on a ſuddaine tenne or twelue reſolute Souldiers, with ſhort ſwords and Piſtolls might chop into it, to hinder the Enemie from faſtning anie fireworkes vpon our Gallerie, which the Enemie perceauing, attempted nothing. The Lorde of Oxford gaue order likewiſe that our Muſketteirs from all flanks ſhould continuallie be playeing, and our Ordinance ſhooting vpon the top of their Bulwarke
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22709:11"/> and their halfe Moone to keepe the Enemie from peeping over and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fire vpon our Workemen. This night although it was Moonelight, the Bruſh and faggots were layd ouer to the left hand of the Bulwarke, from the end of our ſecond Gallerie in the Bleachfeelde, and thanks be to God, but one Man ſhot in layeing them over, and another Souldier of Captaine Skippons ſhot, which ſtood Centinell in our Long Gallerie. My Lord Crauen whoſe worth and liberallitie was knowne heere extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narilie, this night and the daye followeing (as at other times he vſed to doe) watched with my Lord of Oxford, the next night with my Lord Cicills Companie, and the third night with Generall Morgans Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. My Lord of Doncaſter and my Lord fielding trayled Pikes vnder my Lord Cicills Companie, and went conſtantlie downe to the Approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vpon anie ſervice, and expoſed theire bodies both to danger and ſickneſſe. My Lord of Oxford an houre before he was relieued, had a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout with the Enemie vpon the lefte corner of the halfe Moone; and my Lord Veres Muſketteirs of Dort comming vp almoſt to the top of the halfe Moone, gaue fire in the teeth of the Enemy, and came to the puſh of Pike thorow the Blinds, this ſtartled them and made them throwe ſtones and Handgranadoes amongſt our Men, but his Lord cauſed a Souldier of Captaine Roockwoods Companie to caſt 14. Handgrana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does among them into their halfe Moone, which made them giue backe and cry, Guarda, Guarda. The Granadoes being burſt they came vp againe to the top of the halfe Moone, and gaue fire vpon our Men, but my Lord cauſed Muſketteirs to be drawne to the top of our gards, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie that of Captaine Clarke, which was high, they gaue fire apace vpon them, fetcht ſome of them off, which ſhewed their heads and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; this peece of ſervice being ended, my Lord of Oxford being relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued drew awaye to his Quarter.</p>
            <p>On Count Erneſts ſide the 19. of Auguſt the Bruſh and Planks were layd ouer to the Enemies Horneworke, and a Mine made into it: This Mine being ſprung, the Scotſh and the Dutches fell on couragiouſlie, and they and the Enemie gaue fire apace one at another for three quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of an houre, our Ordinance playing from all Batteries as faſt as they could charge and diſcharge; in this time the Enemie ſtood out verie ſtoutlie three aſſaults, with the loſſe of manie men: But the Enemie gaue fire in ſuch manner from the Wall of the Towne, and out of the greate halfe Moone, that our Men were forced to retreate into the mouth of their Gallerie and Works, yet this advantage wee got that wee did ſett vp ſome Muſket-baſkets, and lodge ſome of our men vpon the right corner of their Horneworke, from whence wee began a Sap, and made Blinds towardes their halfe Moone, which after another Mine was ſprung cauſed the Enemie on the 21. of Auguſt to quit it, and ſo retired in their halfe Moone. In this fight were ſlayne Captaine Ramſey, and twoo dayes after a Dutch Captaine, called Captaine Hatton, who carried themſelues very worthilie.</p>
            <p>And when as Count Erneſt had ſtrengthened the Betuw, and all the Cities and places thereabouts, as alſo along the River called the Yſſel, againſt all aſſaults of the Enemie, for the furtherance of which the Prince ſending him daylie more Forces as he could ſpare and raiſe them.</p>
            <p>It happened that vpon the 20. daye of Auguſt theſe glad tydings came to the Prince to wit a Letter from that worthy and Valliant Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Otto de Gendt and Oyen, Lord of Dyden, Gouernor of Emrick, vnto the Prince of Orenge, the tennor whereof followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:22709:11"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE bearer hereof my Coſſen Merode is come to make reporte vnto your Excellentie of the good ſucceſſe of the ſurpriſing of the Citie of Weſel. The Enemie hath likewiſe quitted both the Sconces, making not one ſhot againſt vs. Theire man of warre they haue ſunke themſelues; and hauing a parcell of ſmall ſhipping in the Ryne, I did cauſe parte of them to be burnt, I haue founde greate number of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance heere, and 13. or 14. Boates vpon Karts. And for the better ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this Citie, I haue ſent for more Companies out of Emmerick and Rees: And if it pleaſe your Excellentie, I ſhould deſire more ſtrength. Thus in haſt I take my leaue.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>WESEL <date>the 19. of Auguſt 1629. In the morning betweene 4. and 5. of the Clocke.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your Excellenties humble and faithfull OTTO OF GENDT AND OYEN:</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The firſt Vndertakers of this Enterpriſe were Peter Mulder, Richard Mulder his Brother and Iohn Rootleer all three Burgers of WESEL, men of a meane condition, but of a good ſpirit &amp; reſolution. This Peter Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der divers times fayning to learne to ſwim, had pilde the depth of the moate on that ſide, which he intended the Citie ſhould be aſſaulted, and ſpying out all opportunities, made a greate Iron hammer to beate downe the Palliſadoe, which ſtood vpon the Bulwarke on the Eaſt ſide of the Towne, wherewithall the Prince being aquainted as alſo of the poſſibilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this deſigne. His Excellentie appointed the Lord of Dyden for the mannaging thereof. The time and place being appointed the 18. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, Peter Mulder went out of WESEL at one Gate, and his Brother out of another Gate, about three houres before the ſhutting of the Gates. Peter Rootleer followed a while after, to avoyde all ſuſpition, all three meeting togeather in the darke at the place appointed: And hauing cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the Name of the Lord of Hoſts, for his ayde &amp; aſſiſtance here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that thereby theire fellowe Brethren and Cittizens might be releaſed from the bondage and vexation of theire Enemies. The Lord of Dyden about midnight came vnto them, with ſome ſixteene hundred foote (ſome muſkettiers others firelockes and halfe pikes) and eight Troopes of Horſe. Before they went on the Lord of Dyden to doe noe man wrong, made the Captaines to drawe Billets, who ſhould fall on firſt: And Peter Muller with his twoo Comrades went on before them couragiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. But ere our Troopes came thither, and that the Lord of Dyden had ordered the buſineſſe thus, it began to be light, ſo that they imagined it was not practicable. The Enemie likewiſe ſeeing the daye broke, and that it began to be light, drewe off their By-watch from that place, and betooke themſelues to their reſt: But God, who is the diſpoſer of all things, and giues courage to men, at laſt our men waded through the moate, and entered the Bulwarke. And Peter Muller with his Comrades broke downe the Palliſadoe and made an entrance. The Officers and Souldiers ſeconded him brauelie, and enters the Towne on Sundaye morning the 19. of Auguſt 1629. a little before Sun ryſing, after the guarde was drawne off: And cutting off the twoo gardes next adjoyning to that place with ſmall reſiſtance, bore vp ſtiffe to the Market place. The Alarme was ſo ſuddayne that the Enemies men running too and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22709:12"/> againe to anſwere it knewe not our Men from their owne vntill it was to late for them; for in the meane ſpace Peter Muller got a ſmith and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Bruyniſh Gate, and let in our Horſemen. The Spaniards ſeeing the Cittie loſt fled to the Sconces out of the Towne, which they yeelded vpon Compoſition: The brunt being over the Souldiers fell a plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring got into the Spaniards ſhops, and into bittereſt Papiſts and Iewes Houſes, ranſacks the Nunneries, breakes downe the Images and got an incredible booty, as Count Henry of Berk his plate and chiefeſt Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, Monte Cuculies monie and goodes, which the Emperour had ſent to him, and the Riches which the Crawats had got in the Germane Warrs, and left there behind them for ſafetie in their expedition for the Velu. To conclude, the Foote devyded the ſpoile, and the Horſemen ſhared Bags and Barrells of Rijcxdollers by hatts full: But that which was moſt remarkeable, that Church which they had bolted vp againſt the Proteſtants, that verie Sunday was made a Priſſon for their Officers and Souldiers, till on the morrow they were ſent to Arnhem. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor and Officers ſtanding good for the ranſom of 1042. Souldiers, who the next daye were ſet ouer the Water with their Wiues and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Three of the Enemies Captaines were ſlaine and about 70. Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and we loſt but 9. Men in all. Beſides this there was found in the Towne manie ſmall Barrells of Piſtolls and Rijcxdollers, for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Enemies Army, 46. peeces of Braſſe Ordinance vpon the Walls, and 2. in the Market place, and 2. in the Magaſin, and 2. Morters, Armes as Corſelets, Pikes, Muſkets and Firelockes to arme 5000. men, aboue 1000. Barrells of Powther, beſides this greate ſtore of meale abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Corne and other Victuall, and proviſion for their Army, which the Lord thus deliuered in our handes.</p>
            <p>On the 24. of Auguſt wee had a generall thankſgiving and a triumph throughout the Army, in acknowledgment of the greate goodneſſe of God for the taking of WESEL. The Triumph was made in this manner: Firſt the Muſketteirs were drawne off from all our Guardes, ſaving the Approaches, and out of our Quarters and placed along the inward Line next the Towne ſome ſixe foote diſtant one from another. The Pikes were drawne to the Outline and Outguardes, the reſt ſtood by deviſions in the Quarters, euerie one of them having a Wiſp of ſtrawe vpon the head of his Pike to be ſett on fire, when the ſignall ſhould be giuen. The volley of Muſketteirs ſhould begin at Crevecoeur, where the Princeſſe laye, and ſo to Engelen; from thence along the Men of warre, and the Redoubts by the Buſſeſlote to Monſieur Pinſens Quarter, ſo the French Line, the Approaches &amp; then to the Engliſh, from thence to the Lord of Brederoes Quarter, and ſo along to Count Erneſts Quarter, and ſo to Count Williams Quarter, where it ended betwixt euerie volley, the Cannon, which laye vpon the Batteries of the Outline thoſe, which were drawne out of our Quarters to the heath by the ſtone Gallowes, and thoſe which were in all the Approaches, ſhould be ſhott off. The ſignall was thus, about tenne a clock in the night, when a Granadoe was ſhott into the Towne, then the firſt volley ſhould begin, and the Wiſpes of ſtrawe vpon the heads of the Pikes ſhould be ſett on fire, all which was done accordinglie, and made a braue ſhow. The volley met with a ſtop at the firſt, but when it came to the French Line, to the Approaches, to the Engliſh, the Lord of Brederoes, to Count Erneſts Quarter and Count Williams Quarter, it ranne well, betweene the Volleyes there were about 300. peeces of Ordinance, from Crevecoeur and round about our Army diſcharged. Thoſe of the Towne acknowledged afterward,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22709:12"/> that ſhooting at once with ſo manie Ordinance out of our Approaches into the Towne, did much amaze them, and then they beganne to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue indeed that WESEL was Geux; Though the Governor by all meanes laboured to conceale it from them.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Auguſt the Enemie ſallied forth into the Workes of Count Erneſt, and burnt aboute ſome 20. Poſts of his Gallerie.</p>
            <p>The 26. Newes came to vs in the Siege, that the Enemye had left Amersford, and that the States had layd 1500. Men in it.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye went forth of our Army twoo Companies of Horſe, and 200. Firelocks, which met with a Convoy of the Enemies goeing to Breda, whereof our Men killed ſome, and tooke 40. of them priſoners, and ſome foureſcore faire Horſes, with their Saddles and Piſtolls, and brought them with good ſtore of munition and match into our Campe togeather, with the Lieftennante and the Cornet or Enſigne bearer of the Enemies Troopes, which became ſurtie for the value of the Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, which our Men left behinde them.</p>
            <p>The 30. A Peſant which had carryed Letters too and fro, in and out of the BUSSE, and had beene our Priſoner ſome tenne weekes, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and hanged in the Princes Quarter.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Septemb. the Enemie quitted the Counterſcharfe of their Halfe Moone, which laye before the Vuchter-Gate.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye our men attempted to make a Mine into the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke of the Towne Walls, but could not effect it by reaſon of a peece of Ordinance, which the Enemie had ſunke, wherewithall they ſlew manie of our Men at the end of the Gallerie.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Septemb. Monſieur Stakenbrooke Lieftenant of our Horſe, and the Duke of Bullen with 1000. Horſe, three hundred Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks, and diuers Engliſh and French Muſkettiers taken out of divers Companies, and three halfe French Cannon toward euening were drawne out of our Quarters, and marched that night to a ſmall Towne and Caſtle in Braband, called Endhouen, ſome ſixe houres going from the BUSSE, where ſome 400. of the Enemies Wardgelders, or as wee terme them freſhwater Souldiers, taken on by thoſe of Flanders, who laye lurking there, to ſee if in the night they could haue cutt our Trench vpon the Outline, and let in the water vpon vs, which ſtood blanke without our Entrenchment, by reaſon of the ſtoppage: But his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentie having intelligence of them, prepared this Camiſado for them. They having advertiſement by ſome Countriemen their freinds, of our Mens comming, ſtole awaye in the night and truſted rather to their heeles then to their Armes: Yet they were not gone ſo farre, but the Duke of Bullen with his Horſe overtooke them, and rounds them in a Morrace and by a Ditch, and charging vpon them, ſlew about 70. of them, the reſt cryed out for quarter, and becauſe they were ſuch Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, the Duke was in a quandary whether he would giue them quarter or noe, but at laſt by much entreaty he graunted them quarter, and brought awaye about ſome eight ſcore of them priſoners. In the Caſtle of Endhouen (which our Men tooke in to their poſſeſſion) we found foure Petars made of oken Planks ſome 5. Inches thick, and the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber or briche lined with yron; theſe ſhould haue beene charged with Powther and ſtones, to haue beene diſcharged out of their ſloopes vpon our Trench, and ſo having made a rupture in our Line, haue let a Sea of water to haue drowned and overflowne all our Approaches, theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines were brought likewiſe in Karts to his Excellencie Houſe in his Quarter.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:22709:13"/>
            <p>The 3. wee began to mine vnder the Halfe-Moone of the Vuchter-Gate.</p>
            <p>The 4. wee ſprung a Mine in the Wall of the Halfe-Moone, but never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe wee were not able to lodge in it.</p>
            <p>The ſame daye the Scotch which had the guarde in the Approaches of Count Erneſt, wonne the Raveline running betweene the Horne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke and the Towne.</p>
            <p>On the fifth of Septemb. the Trench and Faggots being layd from the end of our long Gallerie, to the verie foundation of the Bulwarke. The Miners began a Mine thorow the Brickes into it, and diſcouered a Mine which the Enemie had made; neuertheleſſe taking theire courſe another waye verie ſkillfullie, went forwarde being vndertaken by three Engliſhmen to wit Iohn Scot, William Lee and eſpeciallie Richard Priſtman, who had good ſkill in digging and vnderpropping of Colepits in England; who performed it verie well. This commendations one maye giue them that it tooke the beſt effect of any Mine which was euer ſprung before the BUSSE.</p>
            <p>Well then on the tenth of Septemb. being Mundaye betime in the morning, Sir Iacob Aſhly, Lieftennant Coronell to Generall Morgans Regiment, had the commaund that night in the Approaches, and with much a doe a Mine was made in the Enemies halfe Moone before the Gate, ere the Mine was ſprung he ſent a Sargeant with ſix Muſketteirs to the top of the Halfe-Moone, to giue the Enemye an Alarme to bring them on towardes our Mine, and then for feare of endangering our men, he was to retreate backe againe, all which was done accordinglie: The Myne then being blowne vp, tooke but little effect, and made noe greate entrance. After this Sir Symon Harcourts Enſigne was commaunded to fall vp with ſome 30. Muſketteirs to the top of the halfe Moone, and to giue fire among the Enemye, which he did. The Enemye ſtood it out a good while, thinking to drawe on our Men to twoo of their owne Mynes, which were to be ſprung, nowe the Enemyes twoo Mynes being blowne vp, Sir Iacob Aſhly fell vp, and gave order to Sir Symon Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court to fall into the Enemyes Halfe-Moone with 50. Muſketteirs and Pikes more, with his Enſigne and the ſaid 30. Muſketteirs. The Enemye diſputing it a good while, but at laſt Sir Symon and his men beate them vp to their entrance into their halfe Moone by the moate ſide, and there Changed bullets one with another and came to Puſh of pike, and after they had maintayned that place a pretty while he droue them from thence along the moate ſide to a Traverſe which was caſt vp ſome 60. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the ſaid entrance of the halfe Moone, where following them cloſe along the moate of the Towne Bulwarke, and giving fire vpon them at laſt they bid him farewell and retreated into the Towne by Sainct Iohns gate.</p>
            <p>This being done he himſelfe with his men made a ſtand at the entrance into the halfe Moone, where the Enemye ſtood it out till it began to be light and till our men were lodged in the top of the halve Moone, in thoſe places which might moſt offend the Enemye; this was the firſt worke, which was carryed awaye by force of Armes and really diſputed: In this fight Sir Symon Harcourt was fiue times thruſt and ſhott through his clothes, and yet ir pleaſed God he came of well and with honnor: After the Engliſh had thus taken the Halfe-Moone, his Excellencie came downe into the Gallerie and gaue the Engliſh extraordinary thanks for carryeing themſelues ſo well, and rewarded ſome of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with monie: And thus the Enemye on this ſide were ſhutt vp into the Towne.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22709:13"/>
            <p>The ſame night came on Sir Harry Harbourd, Lieftennant Coronell to Coronell Harwood, and relieued Sir Iacob Aſhly, he brought with him for the reliefe, my Lord Veres Companye of Schoonhouen, Sir Harry Harbourds owne Companie, Captaine Gouldwells, Captaine Abrihalls and Captaine Welſons Companies. The Gallerie being gott over 91. Poſts from the end of it, the Bruſh and Planks, and a Blind was layd to the Bulwarke, and the Myne being readie the Powder was cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered, and the trayne layed to it. His Excellentie as mercifull as valliant (to try what the Enemye would doe) gaue order to Sir Harry Harbourd that on Tewſday morning, after the Myne was ſprung in the Bulwarke, our men ſhould fall on, and though they ſhould poſſeſſe the Bulwarke and be Maſters of it, yet they ſhould retire into the Gallerie: The myne being blowne vp tooke good effect, and caſt vp a greate deale of earth and ſtones into the ayre, and ſhattred ſome twoo rodds of our Gallerie in peeces, and made a breach mountable; after this Sir Harry gaue order that Captaine Abrihalls Sargeant (who was ſlayne goeing on) ſhould fall vp to the Breach with his Muſketteirs; that Captaine Welſon ſhould doe the like with 30. men more to ſecond the Sargeant, and Captaine Gouldwell to ſecond them with the Pikes, from the end of the Gallerie; all which was done accordingly, our men falling vp to the Breach gaue fire in the verie teeth of the Enemye, and our other Muſketteirs giving fire from all Guardes and Flanks, and our Ordinance thundring from all Batteries did ſo amaze and ſtartle them, that they quitted the Bulwarke and retreated where it was cut off to the ſkirt of the Wall by the Vuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergate. This being done our men ſtayed a little while vpon the Breach till they diſcharged all their Bandeliers, and till that Sir Harry cauſed them (according to his Excellencie commaund) to retreate againe into the Gallerie, our men being drawne off, the Enemy came againe to the Breach, and caſt vp a little defence of earth, which the mine had blowne vp, and Bruſh vpon it, but our twoo halfe Cannon, which laye vpon the right ſide of our entrance into the Gallerie, beate the earth and Bruſh, which they caſt vp about theire eares, and ſhore off the heads of the Souldiers Pikes, which ſtood there for the defence of their Workemen. This made a terrible Alarme in the Towne ſo that the Bells rung, the Women and Children cryed, the Burgers and Popiſh Prieſts by flockes ran to the Governor, and tould him that nowe or never it was time to liſſen to a ſeaſonable and an honorable Compoſition, for the ſafeguard of their liues and goods: The Governor taking hold of this occaſion ſtrikes his ſaile, and came with the Biſhop Abbot and divers Officers to the Parapet of the Vuchter-Gate, ſending a Drum, which reported that there were ſome Gentlemen of qualitie overwhelmed and ſtifled in the ſpringing of our Myne, and requeſted that they might be ſought for and burryed. His Excellentie then being neere at hand, ſitting in the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie, gaue waye to their requeſt; but as indeed the matter being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: The Drum came vp againe, and requeſted to ſpeake with ſome of our Officers, and tould them that the Governor, Magiſtracy and Clergie in the Towne were mynded to parley with vs; preſentlie after came foure Perſonnes of quality downe the Breach to his Excellencie in the Gallerie, deſyring foure dayes time to writte to the Archducheſſe, and if ſo be they were not releeued within that time, they would deliuer over the Citie vpon Compoſition: But his Excellencie denyeing them this requeſt. They reſolved notwithſtanding to treate vpon a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and Hoſtages were receaued and deliuered on both ſides. In the meane time the Walls of the Citie were blacke of Burgers and Women,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22709:14"/> and Spirituall Perſonnes to take viewe of our doeings and the danger they were in.</p>
            <p>The 13. of September the Commiſſioners, which the Towne had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, dyned with the Prince, &amp; in the afternoone they left their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the Prince &amp; the States, and tooke their reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with them.</p>
            <p>The 14. the Aggreement was concluded to render vp the Citie with the Petler-Sconce to vs, within three dayes after, and ſo accordinglie was ſubſcrybed by both parties. In the meane time came manie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of people out of Holland and other Provinces thereabouts to ſee this famous Siege, with the departure of the Enemie out of the Citie.</p>
            <p>The 17. in the morning the Prince of Orenge appointed all his Army to ſtand in Battle order, in euerie Quarter, eſpecially thoſe of his owne Quarter, as well Horſe as foote, and placed them in this manner: Along Monſieur Pinſens Quarter (where the Enemy was to march thorow firſt) ſtood ſome threeſcore Companies of Footemen, being Scotſh &amp; Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, from Pinſens Quarter along the Hollandes-Dyke ſtood ſome 40. Companies of French, and neere to the verie place where the Enemy was to march out of our Line, ſtood ſome 40. Companies of Engliſh; and without our Line along the heath ſtood ſome 30. Companies of Horſe. This being the Waye which his Excell: had ordered for the Enemy to paſſe thorow. Betweene the Engliſh and French ſtood a greate Batterie of twenty Peeces of Ordinance to playe vpon the Heath, where his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: cauſed twoo Princelie Tents to be ſet vp, for the Princeſſe, the Queene of Bohemia, and the Ladies &amp; Gentlewomen which were there. The Prince ſitting on Horſebacke, with the King of Bohemia and the Prince of Denmarke, and ſome 40. more, whereof moſt of them were Dukes, Earles, Barrons, Lordes, and the reſt Coronells and of the Chiefe Commaunders, beſides this the greate number of our owne Burgers and people, which came thither to, behould this ſight was ſo greate that they could hardlie gett beere for their monnie, and manie of them were faine to ſleepe in the feelde vnder the ſkie for want of better lodgings.</p>
            <p>Nowe to relate the manner of their marching forth: Firſt in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning there marched forth ſome 50. Horſmen, and as manie firelocks and Muſketteirs. Then followed about eleauen hundred Waggons &amp; Karts, whereof ſome 400. of them were loaden with ſicke &amp; mayned Souldiers, and the reſt with goods, houſhouldſtuffe, Images, Clergieme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Women; and about eleauen of the clocke came the Ieſuites &amp; Prieſts ryding vpon Waggons, and ſome barefooted Monkes and Fryers goeing a foote. His Excell: being gone to dinner with the King &amp; Queene of Bohemia, and the reſt of the Lordes and Ladies, which ſtood vpon the Batterie in the twoo Tents. In the meane time came the Governors Wife in her Koach, who was but 3. weekes ould in childbed, accompanied with her daughter and her Child, lyeing vpon the Nurſes lap in the forepart of the Koach. Generall Morgan &amp; ſome others courts her, and made her ſtaye before his Excell: Tent, till he with his trayne returned from din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. His Excell: comming ſaluted her, and had ſome ſmall diſcourſe with her, and then tooke his leaue and let her paſſe. Towardes euening came the Governor himſelfe marching in the midſt of his Troopes, hee ſtaid long becauſe his Cannon was graveld and ſunke into the ground that he could not drawe them away; the night drawing on his Excell: ſent him word by the Sergeant Major Generall that he would ſend them after him on the morrowe. The Governor had ordered his Men by three divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, the firſt were the Walloones conſiſting of ſixe coulouts being ſome 400. Pikes firelocks and Muſketteirs. The ſecond were Burgonians. The third &amp; greate diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were Highdutches with nine coulours.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:22709:14"/>
            <p>Theſe 3. diuiſions were a matter 1400. men: Then followed the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor on Horſebacke, and paſſing by, his Excellencie had ſome ſmall ſpeech with him: After the foote came three Troopes of Horſe, which brought vp the Reare, the firſt was about 70. in number, the ſecond about 80. and the laſt Troope about 90. all well mounted, well armed, proper Men, with red ſcarfes about them. During this Siege the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye confeſſed there were ſlayne ſome eleauen hundred Souldiers, and not aboue 16. or 18. Burgers, by reaſon they refuſed to endanger them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the Outworkes. They had with them according to the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Compoſition three whole and three halfe Cannon, verye faire peeces, and twoo Granado Morters. They lefte beſides theſe in the Towne ſome 36. braſſe Peeces of Ordinance and ſixe Yron peeces, the moſt parte of the Braſſe Ordinance being Sling-peeces and Faukenetts, and fewe halfe Cannons, except ſome which the noſes were bruſed and ſhott off: And little or noe Powder to ſpeake of, which indeed was the principall occaſion they yeelded vp their Sconces, Traverſes, Halfe-moones and at laſt the Citie it ſelfe ſooner then they needed.</p>
            <p>In this Siege there happened manye ſtrange paſſages, which would be too tedious to rehearſe, onelie twoo things of note, I cannot but make the gentle Reader acquainted with firſt in the Croſſebrethren Cloyſter, a little before the Towne was yeelded, there was a Monke in the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill ſitting in one of the Seats of the Quire, and reading in one of his Maſſebookes about midnight, wee ſhott a Granado into the Towne, which fell iuſt into the Seate where he ſate, and tooke him, his Seate and Booke awaye that ſcarſelie they could finde a Mommock lefte of him, onely leauing the tincture of his blood vpon the Wall for a memoriall, which is yet to be ſeene to this daye. The ſecond there was a ſtrange ſhott hapned as in Oſtend, there was a Cannon Bullet of the Enemyes ſhott from the downe Batterie, iuſt into the mouth of one of our Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, which laye vpon the Weſt-Bulwarke charged. Theſe twoo Bullets ſtryking togeather, gaue fire to the looſe cornes of Powder, which were not driuen home: Our Cannon went of and ſent the Enemy their owne Bullet and ours backe to them againe. So before the BUSSE a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers preſenting his Muſket to giue fire vpon the Enemye: The Enemie being quicker then hee, diſcharged firſt vpon him, and ſhott iuſt into the Bore of his Muſket, parte of the lead beating out at the Tutch-hole, and ſo by the prouidence of God this Souldier eſcaped a ſcouring.</p>
            <p>To returne againe where I lefte hauing related vnto you the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Enemye, ſo in the morning about eight a clocke his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie ſent into the Towne his owne Guarde, with ſixe other Companies to take poſſeſſion of the Bulwarkes, and about the euening came in ſome tenne Companies more.</p>
            <p>The 18. all ſtrangers were ſuffred to come into the Towne, and viewe all the Enemyes Workes, Churches and Nonneries, one of them clymed vp to the top of Sainct Iohns Church, ſteeple and ſett an Orenge ſilke Flag aboue the Wethercocke.</p>
            <p>The Burgers for the moſtparte were verie well provyded of all kinde of Victualls, except Cheeſe and Butter. The ſame daye his Excellencie came into the Towne, but returned ſuddenlie backe againe.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:22709:15"/>
            <p>The 19. our Miniſters preached in three of the Churches, and in the greate Church were three Children baptiſed, where the PRINCE OF ORENGE, the King of Bohemia and the Princeſſe of Orenge were Godfathers to them.</p>
            <p>After this his Excellencie placed newe Magiſtrates in the Towne and diſcharged the ould Magiſtrates, and all the reſt of the Burgers of the oath, which they had made to the King of Spaine, and receaued them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the oath of the States of theſe Unyted Provinces. And ſo left the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of Brederode with 36. Companies of foote and 10. Companies of Horſe for Garriſon in the Towne. The States preſcrybing a daye of Thankſgiuing to the Lord throughout the Provinces for theſe Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:22709:15"/>
            <head>ARTICLES Granted by his Ex<hi rend="sup">cie</hi>. my Lord the Prince of Orengie, to the Gouernour of the Buſſe, &amp; the Captaines, Officiers and Souldiers therein.</head>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT the Gouernour of the Buſſe, with all the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of ware, and for diers of what quality, or condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo euer they be; aſwell Horſemen, as foot, none excepted: yea though they haue abandoned the ſeruice of my Lords the States, and giuen themſelues into that of the King of Spaines, ſhal goe out of the Towne without any diſturbance, or moleſtation with their armes and Baggage; The horſe by the ſound of the trumpet, their Cornets diſplayed, armed Compleate, and their Piſtolles in their hands: The foote beating their drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, their Coullers flying, their matches lighted at both ends, bullet in mouth, and in rancke and forme, as they vſe to march in Battaile, with their goods and the ſafety of their liues to the towne of Dieſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>They ſhall carry with them ſixe pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ordinance, and two Morters at the choiſe of the Gouernour, with all their traine, equipage, and munition of warre, ſufficient to diſcarge euery one a duſſen ſhott.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>They ſhalbe furniſhed with horſe, Waggons, and their Conductours ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent to draw Ordinance and Morters with all their trayne and Munition vnto the towne of Dieſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <p>All munitions of warre &amp; of Victualls appertaining to the King of Spaine, ſhalbe deliuered by ſuch as his Excell: ſhall appoint to this effect, ſauing thoſe Victualls which were ſould before the 12. of this moneth, when wee began to treate, which ſhall remaine ſould, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſearch or making inquiry after any man that made any ſaile of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>All Officers and Souldiers, aſwell ſick as hurt in the Geſthouſe or in any other place ſhall remaine there till they haue recouered their healths, and are able to goe away, giuing them ſafe Conuoy and commodity to bring them their Armes and Baggage to the towne of Dieſt or Breda.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>A ſufficient number of waggons and horſe which the Gouernour ſhall requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, aſwell for his perticular ſeruice, as for the Officers &amp; Souldiers to carry their goods and Baggage to Dieſt is graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, comprehending therein all their Armes: yea the ſouldiers of the garriſon of the Towne, abſent ſicke, dead, hurt or fled, and that the ſaid wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons ſhall in noe caſe be viſited.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>Thoſe which will deſire to carty their Goods and Baggage to Antwerpe, ſhall haue boates without any charge to them, to bring them thither thorow Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, freed from all manner of taxes, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, or impoſitions permitting them men to looke vnto their goods and Baggage, which ſhall not be viſited nor ſtayed in any place, vnder any pretence whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, but ſhall paſſe to Antwerpe without diſbarking themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>The Gouernour, Chiefs, Officers mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary, Iudges, Souldiers, and all others receiuing paye from the King of Spai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, aſwel Clergy men as Laye-men none excepted, as alſo the widdowes and children, which haue in the ſaid Towne any houſes, Inheritances, Rents, either vpon the States of Brabant in theſe quarters, or the Towne, or vpon houſes or particular grounds, other goods mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable or immoueable, ſhall haue the ſpace &amp; time of two yeeres after the ſigning of this Treatie, to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſport them, to morgage them at their wills, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to diſpoſe of their goods, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſaid time ſhall enioy their Rents, hyres of houſes, fruites and goods got or to be gotten, of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and condition ſoeuer they be.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>That the Officers an ſouldiers of what
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22709:16"/> charge or condition ſoeuer they be, may leaue their wiues &amp; children in the towne &amp; during this terme of two yee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res may diſpoſe of their goods mouea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and immouable ſituated in the ſaid Towne, or els where none excepted, without any confiſcation or prize to be made of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>That the Officiers and ſouldiers, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their charg and ſeruice within the time of two yeeres, may freely returne into the ſaid Towne, and enioy this Treatie as other Burgers and Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants doe, prouided that firſt they giue notice thereof to his Excell: or the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of the ſaid Towne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>Noe Officers or Souldiers goods or Baggage ſhalbe arreſted here for any debts whether he goes out with the garriſon, or being ſick or hurt, or at his going out when he is recouered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>The priſoners aſwell on the one ſide as on the other, of what Condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be, ſhalbe ſett at liberty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paying of ranſome, but onely for their dyet according to the taxation of the place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>That all the boote made by thoſe of the Towne, aſwell before as during the ſiege, ſhall not be reſtord back by them, but ſhall remaine with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="article">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>After the Articles of this Compoſition are ſigned, time ſhall be giuen to the Gouernour of the Buſſe to ſend an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe meſſenger to the Sereniſſime In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta of Spaine, with ſafe Conduct and aſſurance, to giue her aduice of what is paſt, and it is to be vnderſtood that the Gouernour may doe that the ſame day as the articles are ſigned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="article">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>The Conditions being concluded, two dayes at the leaſt ſhall he giuen to the Gouernour and ſouldiers, to prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re themſelues for their departure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="article">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>The time limited being expired the ſaid Gouernour and Officers doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to depart the garriſon, to wit on Munday next betime in the morning, which wil be the 17. of this preſent mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of September.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="article">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>Yet to be vnderſtood that during the time of theſe two dayes noe man in the Towne may come into the Armie, nor thoſe of the Armie goe into the Towne, and that for the avoyding of diſorder, but euery one in the meane while to keepe themſelues in the trenches and Fortifications, without making of any approach or act hoſtilitie, in aſſurance whereof hoſtages ſhalbe giuen on both ſides.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="article">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>That before the garriſon depart ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Hoſtages ſhalbe giuen on his Excel: behalfe, who ſhall march with the garriſon, Armes and Baggage to Dieſt, and a counter change for them by the Gouernour, which ſhall remaine in the Army, til his Excell: hoſtages and wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons be returned, and aſſoone as they are come back, his Excel: will ſend their hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages with ſafe conduct and aſſurance vnto the Towne of Dieſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="article">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>The Officers, Captaines and Officers, compriſed in the firſt Article of this Treatie, hauing any armes, boates, ſloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes or other preparations of warre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing particularly to themſelues, may ſell or tranſport them, without any en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry to be made about thoſe which ſhall buy or carry them away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="article">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>There ſhalbe noe Reſtitution made of any horſes, marchandiſes, wares or any other goods ſold or held for bootie, nor noe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> called in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about that.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="article">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <p>Thoſe of the garriſon of Breda being in the Towne, aſwell Officers as perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Souldiers, may returne to Breda with the ſafety of their liues and goods, as likewiſe ſhalbe giuen to them a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient number of horſe and waggons, and a hoſtage to carry them and their goods thether in all aſſurance, according to the tennor of the firſt Article as comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded therein.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at the Camp before Buſſe <date>the 14. of September 1629.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>and was ſigned <hi>F. Henry de Naſſau. A. de Grobindonck.</hi>
               </signed> And beneath written
<signed>By his Excell: order <hi>I. Iunius,</hi>
               </signed> And ſealed with his Excell: ſeale of Armes.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="points">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:22709:16"/>
            <head>POINTS Agreed on by his Excellencie the Prince of Orenge, and the Deputies of the High and Mightie Lords the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Generall of the Vnited Prouinces, to the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes, Magiſtracy, and Burgeſes on the City of the BVSSE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt that all Offences, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries, and acts of hoſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, committed hapned, &amp; effectuated betweene this Towne, and thoſe of the vnited Prouinces, aſwell from the beginning of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine troubles, Commotions and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, as likewiſe during this ſiege, in what manner ſoeuer, either in generall, or in perticular, aſwell within, as without, are, and ſhall remayne pardoned, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, and held as if they had neuer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo that at no time any mention, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation, pretence, ſuite or inquiſition in law within or without, for the cauſes aboue ſaid ſhall be made, proſecuted, or layd to the charge of the liuing or heires of the dead, or alſo to any goods belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>That the Inhabitants of this towne ſhall carry themſelues conformable to the Edicts of this Land, enioying the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcientie, as they vſually doe ouer all. And that all Eccleſiaſticall and Clergie men, ſhall depart the Towne within the ſpace of two moneths, beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing themſelues in the meane while ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Edicts of the Land, and may take and carry along with them their moueables, Images, Pictures and Church ornaments.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="point">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>The ſaid Eccleſiaſtickes ſhall enioy during their life the reuenues &amp; fruites of their goods, in ſuch places where they pay Contribution, yet is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, that the Eccleſiaſticall &amp; Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torall goods ſhall fall to the High and Mighty Lords the States Generall, who ſhall haue the diſpoſing of them, aſwell for the profit of the Towne as other wiſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="point">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>That de Nunns and other Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call woemen, may abide in the Tovvne, and ſhalbe maintained during their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues out of the reuenues of their Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, yet remayning in the diſpoſition of the high and mightie Lords de States Generall, vvhether they ſhalbe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated in their Cloiſters, or prouided vvith other dvvellings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="point">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>That alſo all the Inhabitants of this tovvne, aſvvell Eccleſiaſticks, Nunns, as ſecular perſons fled or othervviſe, vvho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they bee, bearing Office in the oath, Gouernment, and ſeruice of his Maieſtie, as ſouldiers or others, the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Brabant belonging to this tovvne or not, their liues and goods ſhalbe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, aſvvell in Generall as particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, if they contrary not the precedent Article.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="point">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>Alſo that this tovvne vvith the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants and Burgers thereof, aſvvell the clergie as laye men ſhalbe receiued and vſed in all gentleneſſe and benignity by the Lords, the States Generall, hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard to liue in all friendſhip and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordance with the other Vnited Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Tovvnes, to trade and traffique one vvith another according to their ancient liberty as is fitting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="point">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>That the High and mighty Lords the States Generall &amp; his Excel: the Prince of Orenge, ſhall vſe exerciſe in the ſaid tovvne, liberty, territories &amp; Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, for ſo much as they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the tovvne, the ſame right and Iuriſdiction as the Dukes and Ducheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Brabant hitherto haue had, and to treate vvith this tovvne ſo and in like manner as the capitall Tovvnes of Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant are vſed to doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="point">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>That this Tovvne, Burgeſſes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
<pb facs="tcp:22709:17"/> thereof, ſhall retaine vvithin the liberty of the ſaid tovvne, all their rights, Cuſtoms freedomes, exemptions, and all other priuiledges, aſvvell gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as particular vvhich they haue enio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed and poſſeſſed a long time before the vvarres, aſvvell by vvater als by Land vvithin and vvith out the tovvne, as in Brabant, Gelderland, Holland, Zeeland, vpon the Rhyne, and other Prouinces, places and riuers, aſvvell taxes, toles of timber, Ingebot, the ſtaple af oxen, and others none excepted, foraſmuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes their lavvfull poſſeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="point">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>That the ruling and gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the tovvne, aſwell for the Adminiſtration of iuſtice, as in politique affaires ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue with the Magiſtrates, and the three members of the Towne, and that noe other perſons ſhalbe promoted the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revnto, or choſen, but ſuch as are natifs of the ſaid towne, or which haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued holy baptiſme there, or ſuch others as the High &amp; Mighty Lords the States Generall ſhall thinke good to natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize and qualifie therevnto: Sauing that for this time the Gouernment both in iuſtice and pollicie, aſwell in chiefe as ſubordinate Magiſtrates ſhalbe abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute appointed and conſtituted by his Excel: &amp; the Deputyes of the high and Mighty Lords the States Generall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="point">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>That the towne ſhall hold in their owne Gouernment and diſpoſition, all their inhabitantes, right of impoſitions, Fiſheries wayes, corne meaſure, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethly monyes, and all their rightes and reuenues in the ſame manner, and as they haue hitherto enioyed the diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ordering of them, prouided that they haue right therevnto, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preiudicing the other membres of the vnited Prouinces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="point">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>Thoſe of the tovvne ſhall keepe ſtill the reſidue of their victualls, materialls and other their common goods ſould for the benefit, and the eaſing of the towne of charge, and preſerued at the diſpoſition of the aboueſaid three mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, except the Ordinance, Armes and other munitions kept for the Towne, which may not be ſould.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="point">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>That all Confraternities, Artilleries, gilds and occupations, being at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the towne, ſhall remaine in eſſe and keepe their ancient Charters, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, &amp; Priuilidges together with all their goods ready or vnready, and to this end in time to come they may be ordered by the ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fraternities, occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, gilds, or ſold or bought by them, and ſo to be gouerned by the Marſhalls headmen, and Rulers thereof for the common good, and to diſpoſe of them according to their pleaſures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="point">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>That in the County of Holland, and other vnited Prouinces the three Armes of this tovvne ſhall not be ſtamped or counterfeited, neither any the markes belonging to the gilds, or occupations of this tovvne, as the Cutlars, the point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, and other hand crafts men, but that euery one ſhall keepe, and vſe their owne propper marke, and that of the townes where the worke-manſhip is made. And that all gilds, and manifactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res as alſo the Dyers &amp; the new yeerely fayres procured during theſe troubles in the maioury of this City ſhall ceaſe, vn leſſe thoſe of the maioury being heard there vpon touching their anuall faires, otherwiſe ſhalbe diſpoſed of in all equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by the High and Mighty Lords the States Generall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="point">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>The Inhabitants of the Buſſe, and thoſe in the country ſitting vnder co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution haue graunted them, and ſhalbe entreated as the other good Inhabitants of the Vnited Prouinces, aſwell within the Towne as Dwellers in the plaine country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="point">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>And for that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernes the Rents, and lawfull debts made by the three members of the city or their Deputies, alſo ordeined by the Magiſtrate, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted to be payed, aſwell during this ſiege as before, vvhether they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovvled or ſealed or noe, the Magiſtrats of the tovvne, ſhall deliuer ouer a perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſtate, that the high &amp; mighty Lords aftervvard may in all equity diſpoſe thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="point">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>And for the payment of them, and all other charges of the Tovvne, the preſent acciſes, impoſitions and other meanes of the Tovvne in future time, ſhall take
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22709:17"/> their vſuall courſe, which may be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or diminiſhed by the three mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: yet ſo as they doe noe preiudice to the meanes vvhich is rayſed for the common vveale.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="point">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>That all acts, Reſolutions, Decrees &amp; Ordinances made by the three members or Magiſtracie, foraſmuch as they doe not contradict the State or good of the United Prouinces, alſo the ſentences gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in power of Iudicature by the Shrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, as likewiſe all euiction of goods duely ſolemnized, ſituated, with in or without this towne, ſhall remaine in their force &amp; vigour, yet ſo as that it be no preiudice of the intereſſed partie, neither vpon the right of appeale, or reformation, if that belongs vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="point">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>That thoſe which are at this preſent in the Magiſtracis, or haue bin hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſhall not be moleſted, not troubled, becauſe of the Acts and Ordinances, graunted by them for the diſtribution or payment of any mony for the Towne, or other Prouiſions made, neither ſhall alſo the receiuers be called to an account for any mony that they haue payed and receiued, nor that the Accounts of the aboueſaid receiuers, and other Deputies of this Towne, ſhallbe ſubiect to any ſearch or riviſion. As likewiſe all the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts giuen vp by the receiuer of the Demaines, States of Brabandt receiuers of licences, Conuoyes, and Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhall continue as they are without any inquity made after them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="point">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>That the gouernment of the table of the holy ghoſt, the great hoſpitall, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of Churches, orphane houſes, Laſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, findlings, madmen, and other foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of Hoſpitall, for men and women, and the authoriſation of the Ouerſeers, and directours of them, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be conferred and giuen by the three members in conformity and according to the Priuiledges of the City and as they haue bene exerciſed heretofore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="point">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>That alſo the owners of winde-mills, &amp; oyle-mills within this towne and the freedome thereof during this ſiege, or which by former warres haue bin broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off, or ſhot downe, or otherwiſe demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, may build them vp againe in the ſame places, without ſuing any new warrants for them, or to paye any other rights, then thoſe which they haue vſed to pay heretofore, except the ſeruice of the Land ſhould otherwiſe require it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="point">
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <p>That euery Layeman of what condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoeuer he be, being in the oath and ſeruice of his Majeſt: of Spaine, whether of the towne or noe, he ſhalbe freely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, after the ſurrendring to depart out of it with his family &amp; goods, and to this ende may ſend for waggons, kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, boates or ſhipping out of Brabant, Holland, and other Newtrall Townes, without any of their perſons, goods, or the conductours of them, either going or comming ſhalbe hindred, moleſted, or troubled by the Souldiers or Fiſcals, or any other, and that without requiring any other paſport or conſent but this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="point">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <p>Moreouer the Burgers departed out of the towne, and ſuch as are deſirous to dwell in the towne, as likewiſe thoſe which haue bin in the ſeruice, oath, mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary of his Majeſt: or not, and the heeyrs belonging to them, ſhall haue three yee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res liberty enſuing that they may in all places, aſwell in the towne, liberty, and maioury thereof, ſell, tranſport, change, barter their goods, as they thinke good and fitting, or to haue them receiued or adminiſtrated by ſuch as ſhall ſeeme beſt to them, and comming dye within or without the towne, during the ſame ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, by will or without making of will, in ſuch a caſe their goods ſhall fall to their inſtituted inheritours, or to the next of their kindred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="point">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <p>And thoſe in the meane time, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the aforeſaid three yeeres, which will goe into the Prouinces &amp; townes, belonging to &amp; vnder the obedience of his Majeſt: about their perticular affaires may freely doe the ſame foure times a yeere, with the former knowledge of the Gouernour, of whome they ſhalbe bound to require a paſport, which he ſhal giue them, vnleſſe he hath ſome iuſt reaſons to the contrary: And at end of theſe three yeeres may make their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in this towne or in other places, where they pay Contribution, where they ſhall enioy the ſame liberty, for to goe, to paſſe, &amp; to traffique euery where, for the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22709:18"/> enioying of the effect of this preſent treaty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="point">
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <p>That noe other Gouernour ſhallbe appointed or made ouer the Towne, nor his Subſtitute, but one of the Houſe of Naſſawe, or ſome other Nederlandiſh Lords of Vaſſalls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="point">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <p>That the garriſons ſhall not enioy any exemption or freedome of impoſition from the meanes of the towne, but ſhall help to beare the acciſe, as other inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="point">
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <p>That all perſons abſent, their wiues and children, aſwell clergy as lay men fled, ſhalbe included, and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this treatie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="point">
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <p>That all ſicke and hurt, at this preſent in the great Hoſpitall or other houſes, either Souldiers or others may bide the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein, till they are thoroughly recouered, or afterward to ſtay or to depart, as it pleaſeth them, &amp; to that end ſhalbe aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with waggo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or carts to carry away their Baggage without any impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="point">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>All theſe Articles are approued, agreed vnto by his Excie &amp; the Deputies of the High &amp; mighty Lords the States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, &amp; accepted on by the Eccleſiaſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, Magiſtrates and Burgers of the ſaid Towne, in power of their letters, or Atturney, in witnes whereof wee haue ſigned herevnto at Vucht in the Campe before the BUSSE the 14. of September 1629.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>And was ſigned
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>F. Henry de Naſsaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fr. Michael Biſhop of the Buſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Fr. Johannes Moore Abbet of Bernes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Johannes Hermanus, Deacon of the Buſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>R. van Voorne. R. van Greeneven.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Blooff van de Sloote. Henry Summars.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Peeter Huberts Herialthuvel.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>THE RATIFICATION.</head>
               <p>THE States Generall of the Vnited Prouinces, hauing heard the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of their Deputies, after the ſight, lecture, and examination of the points and Articles aboue named, haue with ripe deliberation approued and ratified the ſame as their Highnes &amp; Mightines doe approue and ratifie them by theſe, promiſing to keepe &amp; obſerue them, and cauſe them to be kept and obſerued; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the tenour and forme of them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Giuen in the Campe before the BUSSE <date>the 14. of September 1629.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>And was ſigned <hi>Hen. Ter Cuylen. Vt ſupra.</hi>
                  </signed> And vnder eath was written
<signed>By the order of the High &amp; Mighty Lords the States Generall. Signed <hi>Corne. Muſch.</hi> And ſealed with the ſeale of their High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and Mightigeſſes.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at AMSTERDAM, By Ian Frederickſz Stam. M.DC.XXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="map">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22709:19"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>start of three page map</figDesc>
                     <head>Carte, repreſentant les Approches du Quartier du Prince d'Orange juſques aux deux Fortereſſes Iſabelle et S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Anthoyne Par le S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Iaques Prempart Ingenieur du Roy de Swede.</head>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>A</item>
                           <item>B</item>
                           <item>C</item>
                           <item>D</item>
                           <item>E</item>
                           <item>F</item>
                           <item>G</item>
                           <item>H</item>
                           <item>I</item>
                           <item>K</item>
                           <item>L</item>
                           <item>M</item>
                           <item>N</item>
                           <item>O</item>
                           <item>P</item>
                           <item>Q</item>
                           <item>R</item>
                           <item>S</item>
                           <item>T</item>
                           <item>V</item>
                           <item>X</item>
                           <item>Y</item>
                           <item>Z</item>
                           <item>Aa</item>
                           <item>Bb</item>
                           <item>Cc</item>
                           <item>Dd</item>
                           <item>Ee</item>
                           <item>Ff</item>
                           <item>Gg</item>
                           <item>Hh</item>
                           <item>Ii</item>
                           <item>Kk</item>
                           <item>Ll</item>
                           <item>Mm</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22709:20"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>continuation of map</figDesc>
                     <head>Autre Carte, repreſentant la continuation des Aproches du Quartier du Prince d' Orange, depuis la petite fortereſse S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Anthoyne, juſques a la Ville et Boulevard, la ou on a faict ſaulter la derniere Mine, Par le S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Iaques Prempart Ingenieur du Roy de Swede.</head>
                  </figure>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22709:22"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>continuation of map</figDesc>
                     <head>LES APPROCHES DV COMTE GVILLAVME DE NASSAV.</head>
                  </figure>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:21"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of the approaches of Count Erneste Casimir on Bois le Duc</figDesc>
                  <head>Les Approches du Comte Erneſte Caſimir de Nassau, Gouverneur de Friſe, Mareſchal gen: du Camp devant Bois le Duc.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:23"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of the approaches of Baron Brederode on Fort de Petteler</figDesc>
                  <head>Les APPROCHES DV BARON DE BREDERODE vers le Fort de Petteler.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:24"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of the approaches of Sr. Pinsen</figDesc>
                  <head>LES APPROCHES DV S<hi rend="sup">R</hi>. PINSEN Gouverneur de Rees. <hi>Amſtelodami Henricus Hondius Excudit. Anno 1630.</hi>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:25"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of the district of the Count of Solms</figDesc>
                  <p>CARTE contenant le Quartier du Comte de Solms a Engelen, avec les Moulins a eau faict par le commandement du Prince d'Orange, et autres ouvrages d'alentour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Amſterodami, HENRICVS HONDIVS EXCVDIT. Anno 1630.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22709:26"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>four scanned partial images of one map</figDesc>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22709:27"/>
                  <p>Nouvelle Carte repreſentant la Ville de BOLDVC en plan, avec ſes Rempars, Foſſez, Fortereſſes d'alentour <hi>etc.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Enſemble</hi> Les APPROCHES de cha<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Quartier de ceux de dehors juſques a la dite Ville.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>tout Meſuré et Deſsigné, Par le S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Jaques Prempart, Gentilhomme Francois, Ingenieur du Roy de Swede.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
